<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dayly exercyse and experyence of dethe, gathered and set forth, by a brother of Syon Rycharde Whytforde</title>
            <title>Dayle exercice and experience of dethe.</title>
            <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1537</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 117 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 159:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dayly exercyse and experyence of dethe, gathered and set forth, by a brother of Syon Rycharde Whytforde</title>
                  <title>Dayle exercice and experience of dethe.</title>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[132] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Joh[a]n waylande, at London within temple barre. At the sygne of the blew garlande, frome the temple gate not farre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An[no] M.CCCCC. [et] xxxvii. [1537]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>An edition of: A dayly exercice and experience of dethe.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through; H10v, final leaf, stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:1"/>
                  <p>¶ A dayly exercyſe and experyence of dethe / ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and ſet forth, by a brother of Syon Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Whyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of a skeleton stabbing a man</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Vnto the deuout reders.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N our lorde god, &amp; mooſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon. This lytle tretie, or draght of deth, dyd I wryte more then .xx. yeres ago / at the requeſt of the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Mother Dame Elizabeth Gybs / whome Ieſu perdon / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abbes of Syon. And by the oft callyng vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and remembraunce of certeyne of hyr deuout ſyſters. And nowe of late I haue ben compelled (by the charytable inſtance and requeſt of dyuers deuout perſones) to wryte it agayne &amp; agayne. And bycauſe that wrytynge vnto me is very te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyouſe: I thought better to put it in print / wherunto I was the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moued / that I perceyued by the prynters: you haue thankfully
<pb facs="tcp:5373:2"/> taken ſuche other poore labours: as we before haue ſende forth. Rede this I pray you ones ouer &amp; after as you lyke it is but very ſhort: and therfore haue I not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded it into chapytours: but only into .ii. partes. In the fyrſt parte wherof is intreated of the fere / or drede of deth to be excluded, exiled, and vtterly put awaye. In the .ii. parte is put forth. The dayly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe and experyence of deth.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the dayly exercyſe of deth the fyrſt parte, whiche is of the feare or drede of deth / to be excluded, exyled and to vtterly be put away.</head>
                     <p>REuerende Mother, and good deuout ſiſters: you haue (many &amp; oftentymes with great inſtance) requyred me to wryte vnto you ſome breue / or ſhort leſſon of deth,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:3"/> and howe you ſhulde prepare and ordeyne your ſelfe dayly therunto. This leſſon is very ſhort &amp; playne after ſaynt Auguſtine:<note place="margin">De te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſerm. ii. c. xxxix.</note> for he ſayth, the leſt leſſon and the beſt meane to dye well: is well to lyue. For who ſo well lyueth (ſaythe he) may nat euyll dye. Then done, we lerne to dye well / whan we lerne well to lyue / and that leſſon can you teche me better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I you. For you haue longer vſed the crafte: and gyuen more dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therunto. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge ſomwhat in parte to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfye your deuout myndes: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what / after our poore vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge: ſhall we ſay. But fyrſt (as ſemeth vnto me) it is neceſſarye &amp; ſpedefull that we inforce and gyue dilygence to auoyde, exclude, exyle, and put ferre away: that chyldyſſh vayne and folyſſh feare, and drede of deth, that many perſones haue: for doubtles it is both vayne and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:3"/> folye: to feare &amp; drede that thynge: that by no meane, may be auoyded &amp; yet ſome perſones ben ſo a frayde of deth / that they ſhrugge, tremble and quake, whan they here ſpeke therof: and renne or departe out of company / bycauſe they wyll nat here tell of dethe. And to excuſe theyr folye they take auctoryte of Ariſtotle the great Philoſophour:<note place="margin">iii. Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ca. i. tra ii. M. xxvi. d. Mar. iiii. d. L. xxii. T ii. Co. v. a.</note> that ſayth: that of al terryble thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, deth is moſte terryble / &amp; ouer that our ſauyour byfore his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, was afrayde of deth, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally dyd abhorre it: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne therof. Saynt Paule ſayth alſo / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wolde nat be ſpoyled of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes / and yet wolde we haue the clothynge of immortalyte vpon whiche / and apon lyke auctorytes they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that deth is peynfull, and therfore to be feared and dred. For declaracyon hereof: you muſt vnderſtande that the drede of deth
<pb facs="tcp:5373:4"/> may be taken .ii. wayes, for .ii. cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / one for the payne that is in the departynge of the ſoule / and the body by deth. And an other waye / or cauſe: for the vncertente of the houre of deth and of the ſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſon in that houre, or tyme. This feare &amp; drede of deth ſhulde euery perſon haue euery houre. But as vnto the fyrſt feare that is for the drede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne in deth, that feare is vayne. For in deth is no payne, or ryght lytle to be feared / as after we ſhall ſhewe. Aryſtotle ſayth in dede:<note place="margin">Vbi ſu.</note> that deth is terryble &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / but that is vnto them alone (ſayth he) that doubt of any other lyfe after this preſent lyfe. <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>
                        </label> yet ſay they: that euery man doth abhorre and lothe dethe: and dothe what he can, to auoyde deth / and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe lyfe / and that is generall in all lyuynge thynges / vnto that I ſay, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwe∣re. </seg>
                        </label> that nature dothe worke / and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:4"/> cauſe in all thynges: the appetyte and deſyre to be contynued and to endure: and laſt for euer / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto dethe infors as muche as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may / other in them ſelfe or in theyr frute and kynde. But therof doth nat folowe that any peyne is in deth: ne any feare or drede to be takyn therfore. As by example of trees and frutes as well as of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble beſtes. The trees when they wexe olde, don naturally put forth newe ſprynges from the rote: and the frutes: when they be grene and yonge: wyll nat departe from the tree: nor the ſedes from the herbe / or grayne, excepte vyolence: but when they ben full rype / then wyll they naturally of them ſelfe / and by them ſelfe departe without any vyolence. So is it in man: after a lyke maner: that when the perſon is in nature yong: grene, luſty, and ſtronge / and in the body confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:5"/>
/ and lyke ſtate of complexcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: deth is then horrible hugſum, and fearefull vnto the perſone by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is then vyolent. But when the perſone is full rype: that is to ſay / worne by age, or ſekenes, vnto the point of deth. Then is nat deth vnto that perſon, any thynge loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, fearefull, ne peyneful / but ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſwete, pleaſant, and deſyrous: and ſo ſayth Aryſtotle in his boke of naturall philoſophye.<note place="margin">Phi. v.</note> Mors ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, dulcis eſt. Iuuenum vero: violenta. The dethe of aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones (ſayth he) is ſwete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte / but the dethe of yonge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones: is vyolent and greuous / yet ſay I: that the feare is nat for the peyne of deth in departynge of the ſoule. For then is no peyne / but all the peyne is in the ſekenes diſeaſe / and affliccyon before dethe. For the perſones that (as I ſayde) ben worne or waſted vnto the poynte:
<pb facs="tcp:5373:5"/> done dye, and departe this life: nat only without ſorowe or peyne: but alſo with gladnes, ſwetnes, and pleaſure. And ſo ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophour Aryſtotle in an other boke.<note place="margin">Ariſtot. de vita &amp; morte. &amp; Cicero .i. Tuſc.</note> And ſo dothe alſo an other greate philoſophoure / and lerned Tullie. And I dare well ſay, that in dethe is leſſe peyne vnto ſuche perſones: then is in the prycke of a pynne, or nedyll vnto a whole per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone. The feare than that our ſaui-had before his paſſyon / was nat for the peyne of deth: but it was of the fraylte of our nature in his car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall fleſſhely parte for the paynes that he knewe wel ſhulde precede / and go before dethe. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peyne doth our ſenſualyte / and our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parte / alway abhorre / &amp; feare naturally: all though in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones more / and ſome leſſe. For you may ſe in experyence / that ſome ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones ben redy to ſwone or talme / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:6"/> yf they ſe an other ꝑſone ſore wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / blede, or put vnto great pey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / &amp; ſome done ſhake for feare / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they here tell howe ſome other perſones ſhal be racked, and ſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And ſome perſones wyll ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to loke vpon the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or ingyns of tourmentrye: as chyldren whan they ſe the rodde, or whyppe. Deth therfore is nat to be feared / nor dredde for any peyne that is therin. Many done dye, &amp; departe this lyfe: nat onely (as we ſayd) without peyne / but alſo with deſyre, and pleaſure. Which thyng we haue before,<note place="margin">Probacy on by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.</note> proued by auctory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and good reaſon / wyll conclude the ſame. For yf peyne be in dethe / that peyne muſte nedely be / other in the body, or in the ſoule. But in the body (at the poynte of dethe) is no peyne. For than ben all the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and wyttes of the body: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhulde feale peyne or pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:5373:6"/>
/ gone and departed: &amp; the bodye than in ſuche caſe (as for fealynge peyne) as whan it is full dede. And as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule / deth is nat peyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full but rather pleaſant, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / as a perſon that long had ben in priſon / and then were ſodenly louſed and put at lyberte.<note place="margin">De bono mortis.</note> For (as ſaynt Ambroſe ſayth. The ſoule is in priſon / whyle it is in the body, &amp; therfore is it glad to be delyuered by deth. And to ſaye trothe, whan the poynt of deth approcheth and draweth nere bothe the partes (in maner) ben glad to deꝑte in ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre / that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wſe they cal in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> .ii. houſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d men that done tyll their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de together</note> the ſoule from the body / &amp; the body from the ſoule / as by example of .ii. marowes or .ii. ſuche perſones that muſte nede la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour bothe together vnto ſuch an effecte / &amp; purpoſe / as can nat come to pas and be fulfylled by one of them alone / then at nyght, or when theyr purpoſe is ended, they ben
<pb facs="tcp:5373:7"/> gladde,<note place="margin">wher the tone is nat able theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out helpe</note> to depart vnto theyr owne propre whomes, logynges and pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. So is it of the ſoule, and the body / that here as .ii. marowſe or mates done labour to gether as in an exyle or ſtraunge countrey (for as ſaynt Paule ſayth) non habemꝰ hic ciuitatem manentem / we haue nat here (ſayth he) any cytie or dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge place / and whan that labour of them bothe to gether hathe ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled the courſe of nature vnto the periode / &amp; poynt aſſygned of god / than done they gladly depart eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryche towarde his propre whome / that is, the bodye vnto the erthe, from whens it came.<note place="margin">Gene. iii. d.</note> And the ſoule vnto heuyn / except it be letted with any ſynne, which may neuer entre into heuen. Thus haue we proued vnto you bothe by auctoryte and by reaſon / that in deth is no peyne, and ſo that no feare ſhulde be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of any, or for any ſuche peyne.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:7"/> yet ſhall I go forther, and proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by experyence.<note place="margin">Probacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryence</note> For lady expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryence hath ſhewed oftymes / vnto many perſones, that in dethe is no peyne. For ſome perſones haue ben in traunce / that for the tyme haue had a large experyence of dethe / whan the body was ſo deſolate of the ſoule / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body felt nothynge ne any thynge perceyued by any of the ſenſes, or wyttes / and yet hath the ſoule (in the ſame tyme) ſene / &amp; perceyued the ſtate of heuen, hell, or any other place.<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xii. a.</note> Saynt Paule was ſo in ſuche rapte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coulde nat tell him ſelfe whether the ſoule was in his bodye, or nat. And that was a large and nere experyence of dethe / but yet nother he, ne any of thoſe ſo takyn in trau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or rapt / haue made any mencyon of any peyne in theyr rapte: ergo there is no peyne in deth. Swonynge alſo or talmynge / is (in maner) a dethe / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:8"/> ſyth the body (for that tyme) is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytute / and voyde of all the wyttes and ſome in ſuche ſwones, talmes, done expyre, dye, and departe this lyfe. yet thoſe that done ſuruyue / recouer, &amp; lyue agayne / done euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhewe what peyne they had, or ſuffred / that ſo departed in theyr ſwone, or talme / but they confeſſe / and ſay playnly: they felte no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of payne / but rather a greate eaſe of all peynes: ergo in dethe is no peyne. Some ꝑſones alſo haue expyred and dyed ſlepynge (which I doubt nat) ſhulde haue ben wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yf a pynne or a nedell had ben thraſte, or put through theyr eares or yf fyre had brent theyr fynger / ergo no peyne in deth. Let vs yet go vnto a forther experyence of deth.<note place="margin">Io. xi. d.</note> Lazare brother to Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene and Martha (as the Goſpell ſheweh) was dede .iiii. dayes, and yet reyſed by our ſauyour (&amp; many
<pb facs="tcp:5373:8"/> haue ben reyſed by myracle. I knewe, and ſpake with one ſuche my ſelfe. But nothynge haue I herde / or redde of any peyne that any of them ſuffre in dethe / ergo, no peyne in deth,<note place="margin">Amb. de bonomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis &amp; .ii.li. de Cain et Abel. cap. x.</note> and ſo doth ſaynt Ambroſe plainly / affyrm in a boke that he wrote of the goodnes and profyte of dethe. The feare (ſayth he) that the frayle perſones haue of dethe / is rather by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opinyon that they conceyue of deth / then for the ſelfe deth. Bycauſe they haue ſene, or herd tell of many great paynes, ſyckeneſſes, and paſſyons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many done ſuffre before theyr dethe / and that cauſeth theyr frayle fleſſhe to abhorre,<note place="margin">De bona mortis. cap. viii.</note> and to lothe deth / bycauſe of thoſe peynes and greues. And ſpecyally ſuche perſones as haue a loue inordynate vnto the vayne pleaſures of this preſent lyfe. And thoſe alſo, that i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a whole body, haue a ſycke ſoule / &amp; foyled conſcyence &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5373:9"/> moſte done they feare dethe, that halte and ben faynte in the faythe. And no meruayle thoughe ſuche maner of perſons do feare,<note place="margin">In tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vbi ſup.</note> &amp; drede deth. For (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lerned Cicero ſayth) yf theyr lyfe had nothynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ne done / that were to be feared, they ſhulde of dethe haue no drede: wyſe men done feare ſynne, whiche is the acte / and dede of quycke, and nat of dede perſones.<note place="margin">De bono mortis. vt ſupra.</note> We ſhulde (ſayth ſaynt Ambroſe) feare &amp; drede our life / the actes and dedes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, done appertayne and belonge vnto our ſelfe / and ben i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our owne power and at our owne will / &amp; nat feare dethe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is nother in our wyll, ne power. For whether we wyll or nat: that is / wyll we, nyll we expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and dye / nedely we muſt.<note place="margin">De reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u it coru &amp; Cice. vbi ſupra.</note> Than (as we ſayd before) as the wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seneke ſaythe / it is great foly to feare and drede that thynge / that by no meane maye be eſcaped ne
<pb facs="tcp:5373:9"/> auoyded. And who ſo euer wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in ſuche feare or drede,<note place="margin">Cicero vbi ſup.</note> ſhal neuer lyue in quietude and reſt of mynde. Wyſe men ſayeth Cicero / done nat feare dethe / but rather done they contemne, diſpyſe dethe / &amp; ſet nought therby / which thynge doutbles, doth moch auayle, ꝓfet,<note place="margin">In tuſc. vbi ſup.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; ſtrength any perſon whan ſo euer deth ſhall approche, drawe nere, and happe vnto hym / ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if he be a feythfull chriſtyane.<note place="margin">Cicero vbi ſup.</note> For who ſo euer nat onely bycauſe deth is neceſſarye, and can nat be auoyded / but alſo bycauſe that in deth is nothyng to be feared / doth diſpyſe &amp; ſet nought by deth / that perſon / ſayeth he / ſhall for a ſurete haue a great ſuccoure and helpe, here to lyue quietly / and whan the tyme ſhall come, to receyue dethe gladly / and after this preſent lyfe ioyfully to lyue / and bleſſedlye.</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Note here howe great courage
<pb facs="tcp:5373:10"/> and conforte this pagane gyueth men, to diſpyſe / and nothynge to feare dethe. Well ſyr, ſay you / this is ſoone ſayd, or ſoone ſpoken. But yet is nat dethe ſo ſoone diſpyſed / ne ſo lyghtly ſet at nought. For we ſe, &amp; beholde many men / that ſhuld haue ſtronge hertes, &amp; more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes than we women, and ſuch alſo that ben taken, &amp; ſuppoſed for wyſe &amp; well lerned men / that ben moche affrayde of deth. Ah good ſyſters / you muſte conſydre and call vnto mynde / that men ben made of the ſame metall, that women ben / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> amonge them ſome ben as feynte herted as women / &amp; therfore take no hede vnto them.<note place="margin">Cicero i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuſcu. vt ſupra.</note> For althoughe a bolde and hardye herte do moche helpe vnto the contempte, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſynge of dethe / yet maye you by the examples and counſels of holy fathers / ingender &amp; make in your ſelfe a more ſtronge boldnes and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:10"/> hardyneſſe ſpirytuall therunto / &amp; ſpecially by conforte and counſell of holy ſcripture / whiche, as a phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicyon, dothe cure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feynt and feble hertes, withdraweth all vayne &amp; frutles cures and cares / and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuereth the frayle herte / from the delectable poyſon of all worldly &amp; fleſſhely pleaſures / and ſo putteth awaye all feare and drede.<note place="margin">Vbi ſup.</note> Reaſon alſo, as they ſaid Cicero ſaith, doth nat lytle auayle vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempte of dethe, whiche as it were by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne preceptes, or reules doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme / &amp; reyſe up the feynt cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douſe herte. But aboue &amp; beyonde all thinges, whole and pure fayth, ſtronge and ſtedfaſt hope and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte feruent charyte / done moſte helpe thereunto. For theſe do nat onely exyle, exclude, and putte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all feare and drede of dethe with the mooſt hyghe contempte therof / but alſo done ingendre and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:11"/> gette a feruent couetous deſyre of dethe.<note place="margin">Philip. 1.c.</note> Saynt Paule vnto wytnes ſayenge. Cupio diſſolui, et eſſem cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſto / I couet, ſayeth he, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre / to be diſſolued and departed from this lyfe, to be with Chryſte / for faythe dothe teche, aſſure, and gyue certayne knowledge of an other lyfe to come after this lyfe which ſhall be more pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paracyon, than this lyfe is. For to ſay trouth in this lyfe is no maner of pleaſure,<note place="margin">Amb. lib. ii. de. Cai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t Abel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>api. x. Auguſti. Catho.</note> without ſome maner of paſſyon or payne goynge before, or folowynge after. And therfore ſaynt Auguſtyne ſayet / it ſhulde rather be called a deth than a lyfe / &amp; contrarye this deth ſhulde be called lyfe / becauſe it is the ende of all dethes (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye) the ende of al myſeryes / all ſorowes, all ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſes, all diſeaſes, all troubles / all paynes whiche in them ſelfe ben dethes.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mbroſi s de b o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. capi-viii. et. Boetius de cooſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione. i. i. Cor. xv</note> And alſo becauſe it is nat onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of all euylles / but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:5373:11"/> the begynnynge of all that is good as of all felicyte, ioye, gladnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, and pleaſure / &amp; of lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge. For as by this wretched lyfe is one paſſage vnto dethe / ſo by this dethe / is oure retourne vnto lyfe / for yf we ſhulde neuer expyre and dye / we ſhulde neuer ryſe to lyfe agayne. And yf we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ryſe, we ſhuld neuer be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our bodyes / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes &amp; paynes that we done here ſuffre in them for the loue of god.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv</note> And if that were true / than were we, as ſaynt Paule ſayeth / in more myſerable ſtate, and in wors caſe than any other people. But our faythe doth make vs ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where we ſay. Carnis reſurrectionem / that is to ſay, I beleue the reſurrexion of our fleſſhe and bodyes / as in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune Crede. Hope alſo doth helpe moche vnto the diſpyſyng of deth.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:12"/> For whan a perſon hath full fayth that god maye and can do all that he wyll / &amp; that he is of ſuche good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that he dothe loue vs all: than doth hope folowe that faythe / and ſo dothe verely truſt and byleue to haue (after or in the ſayd reſurrexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) euerlaſtyng rewarde, and that rewarde ſhall be good and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, ioyouſe and confortable. It ſhall be a great rewarde, as moche as may be deſyred or gyuen / it ſhal be all god hym ſelfe. And this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde than muſte nedely cauſe a great loue, that is charyte, &amp; very charyte / and loue dothe nat onely diſpyſe deth / but alſo cauſeth a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſyre therof. Here ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es done ſaye ſyr / yf we were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and ſure of that rewarde after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> deth / we ſhuld ſet lytle by deth, and be content and glad to depart: wherunto I ſaye, that all we may be ſure therof, yf we wyll our ſelfe.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:12"/> For our lorde hath frely gyuen vs that grace,<note place="margin">Auguſti.</note> that we may wyll and ſo wyllynge &amp; diſpoſynge our ſelfe therunto: he may nat of iuſtyce / ne wyll of his goodnes withholde it from vs.<note place="margin">Diuus Thoma. i. ſent.</note> That rewarde tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and promyſed vnto them that loue hym / &amp; done worke there after. Well ſyr ſay you, it is harde ſo well to worke in this lyfe / that we may come vnto that rewarde without payne, after this lyfe: and that payne is it / that feareth vs more, than dothe the payne of deth / and cauſeth vs to be ſo lothe to dye, and departe hens. For we wolde lyue lenger to amende our lyfe, and to do penaunce to auoyde or (at the leaſt) to minyſſhe &amp; make leſſe that payne. Vnto this I ſaye true penaunce done for the loue of god / may as well in ſhort tyme as in longe, auoyde or minyſſhe that payne / as is euydent in hym that
<pb facs="tcp:5373:13"/> hange by our ſauyour on the croſſe vnto whom he ſayde. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Hodie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum eris in Paradiſo. Thys day ſhalt thou be with me in paradyſe: it is than nother the longe tyme: nor the ſhort: nor yet the penaunce that dothe put away: or make leſſe that payne of it ſelfe: but the loue of god / for whoſe ſake that penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is done, and that loue may be in a perſone feruente in ſhorte tyme as well as in longe / and all the penaunce that is done,<note place="margin">Grego. probatio a mortis.</note> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but a profe of that loue / &amp; ſo as longe as we byde in this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptyble ſory bodye we muſt loue / and euer proue that loue by conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall penaunce and good werkes forſakynge all ſynne. For els is all the penaunce &amp; the workes voyde and loſte. But yet foloweth nat therof that we ſhulde deſyre longe lyfe ne ſhorte, but as he wyll. For to gyue vnto god frely, fully, and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:13"/> holly our wyll / ſo that we haue no wyll but his, is the greatteſt gyfte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can gyue vnto god, and the thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he chefely requireth &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyreth of vs / for he doth nat deſyre our affliction ne penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but gyue me ſaith he thyne hert: &amp; that ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me. Than ſo to gyue vnto him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fyrſt gaue frely vnto vs: that is fre wyll, is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng that may beſt auoyde or make leſſe that payne. And ſo to ſay, thynke, &amp; wyl that yf he wolde haue vs longer in payne / we ſhulde conſent and wyll ſo to be / &amp; yet forther, we ſhuld ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe &amp; deſyre payne ꝑpetuall after his wyl: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioy euerlaſtyng, contrarye vnto his wyll. And this wil may be had i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fewe yeres &amp; ſhore tyme. To wyll than,<note place="margin">Marcu. triſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g. ad E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pium.</note> and to deſyre to be with god / by longe or ſhorte payne or withoute any payne, as beſte ſhall pleaſe hys gracyous goodnes / is the beſt meane, nexte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:14"/> remedy and mooſt ſure waye to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde, fle, and to minyſſhe payne / and in that wyll (without feare, &amp; drede of deth / or rather diſpyſynge deth) to tary, byde / &amp; in euery thing to ſuffre his wyll &amp; pleaſure / euer redy for dethe, and lokynge euery houre for deth, with ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſyre / and wyſſhe to be with hym, and to abyde here / for nothynge, but only for hym / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be (as ſaynt Paule ſayth) all our lyfe / and deth (for his ſake) be vnto vs lucre,<note place="margin">Phil. i.</note> gaynes, wynnynge and auauntage. The pagane Cicero ſayeth,<note place="margin">In Tuſ.</note> that a wyſe man wyll neuer feare dethe. The reaſon why is: that deth by reaſon of vncertayne chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, doth dayly and hourely fall happye, &amp; ſodenly come vnto euery ſorte / degre, and maner of ages / and alſo becauſe of the ſhortnes of our lyfe, dethe can nat be longe abſent from vs. For (as ſaynt Ambroſe ſayeth) we may
<pb facs="tcp:5373:14"/> be in certente: that yf we lyue very longe: yet ſhall we dye ſhortly.<note place="margin">De bono mortis. ca. i. &amp; ix.</note> For the longeſt of our lyues, is very ſhorte / and ſpecially, yf we compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it vnto the longe life of eternite: than is it nothynge nat ſo moche: as one mote vnto the whole erthe / yet the commune people, whan a yonge perſon departeth doth ſaye: oh alas,<note place="margin">Vbi ſu.</note> it is pytie that ſuch a ꝑſon ſhuld dye thus, and departe before his tyme / but hereunto he doth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Before the tyme, ſayeth he / what tyme done they meane? other that tyme that they wolde ſet and deſyre: or els that tyme that god hathe determyned and appoynted? If they meane theyr tyme, I wyll nat diſpute ne reaſon with them. But if they meane goddes tyme / than wyll I ſaye / that almyghtye god dothe nat gyue lyfe vnto any ꝑſon for euer / as his owne thyng: but rather dothe lende it. As dette to
<pb facs="tcp:5373:15"/> be payde, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer it ſhalbe ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and nat at any certayne day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed / and as the detter may vſe the dette ſo lent, whyle he hathe it / and yet hath no wronge, although it be axed ſoner than he wolde, or yet than he ſuppoſed. So in lyke maner god hath lent euery perſon lyfe, but he poynted no daye whan he wyll axe and haue it agayne / &amp; that he dyd bycauſe he wolde that man ſhulde be alway redy to paye, whan ſo euer he were called vpon. Howe than may any perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne or grudge, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer he is taken by deth / ſyth he receyued life by that condicyon. yet ſyr ſayd they / the credytour and lender is called harde, that calleth for the dette be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the borower haue any gaynes, or profet therof / &amp; ſo done we thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that god dealeth hardely with the yonge perſones / becauſe he taketh theyr lyfe, before they haue any
<pb facs="tcp:5373:15"/> pleaſure thereof. Hereto nowe (ſaye I) they done ſuppoſe (by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure) that is nothynge trewe / that is, that in this lyfe ſhulde be pleaſure / whiche in very dede well conſydered, is contrarye (that is to ſay) diſpleaſure, payne, miſerie, wo, and dethe. And therfore thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones that come to dethe in theyr youthe / ben moch bounde to tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke our lorde: that hath delyuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from thoſe incommodytes and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes, that they ſhulde haue had and ſuffred in lenger lyuynge. And here the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune people ſuppoſe an other great errour, that is / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> longe lyfe ſhulde be good and pleaſaunt, where in dede longe lyfe taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all maner of goodes &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this lyfe / that is to ſay, the goodes of fortune / as landes, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyons, golde, ſyluer, and other goodes, and cattell. For age in longe life ſpendeth all / and getteth
<pb facs="tcp:5373:16"/> nothynge. It taketh away alſo the ſenſes and wyttes of man / as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge,<note place="margin">Cicero vbi ſup</note> ſyght, ſmellynge, taſtynge, and touchyng / with the other goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of nature: as youthe, ſtrength, beaute, and agilyte / nymleſſe and quickenes. And yet the goodes that ben more precyous and dere than al theſe: that is to ſay, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and remembraunce / reaſon &amp; vnderſtandynge, connynge, and knowlege / &amp; maketh many tymes the wyll frowarde. And doth ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre and make whole man, bothe in ſoule and body: full dull in deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and in all maner of goodnes and vertue, wherfore the wyſman ſayd.<note place="margin">Ec. vi. b.</note> Better is he and more happy that dyeth at the mothers wombe forthwith after his byrth / than is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyueth longe. No perſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of any age hath wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge by deth for euery perſon (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e) is in the fyrſte day of byrthe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:5373:16"/> in the fyrſt day of lyfe mortall and ſubdued vnto deth / and in the fyrſte daye of lyfe, euery perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth to dye.<note place="margin">Auguſti.</note> And therfore is it nat agayne the lawe for any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dye at any tyme, yonge or olde. Let vs therfore (good deuout chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyanes) put clene away and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exyle this frayle and fals opiny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deth / and let vs thynke vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and beleue / that in dethe is no wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, but all ryght: no payne, but great pleaſure,<note place="margin">In tuſ. vbi ſup.</note> all good &amp; nothyng euyll. For (as the oftſayde Cicero ſayth) howe may that thyng be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any perſon euyll, and hurt? that almyghty god hath ordayned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all perſones indifferentlye / for theyr good and profet: and as the ende of all euyles? Good lorde, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> howe curragyouſly &amp; gladly ſhuld that iourney and voyage be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſed &amp; taken / whiche ones made and finyſſhed no care, ne woo / no
<pb facs="tcp:5373:17"/> thought ne buſynes / no turmoyle, ne trouble, no ſtryfe ne debate / no payne, ne diſeaſe / no vexacyon, ne diſpleaſure may remayne ne folow but vnto them that well hope / ſhal wel happe / what tyme ſo euer they go. But yet ben they moſt happye / and gracyouſe, that (in ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon) done dye, and departe this lyfe, in theyr youthe / and ſtrength. For vnto them (immedyately after theyr deth, muſt nedely folowe one of theſe twayne (that is) that they muſt go ſtreyght way vnto heuyn: or els vnto payne. If they go vnto payne / than the ſoner they dye / &amp; the ſhorter tyme they lyue: the leſſe there, and the ſhorter tyme ſhall be theyr payne. And ouer that they ſhall haue the greatteſt comforde that any creature may haue beyng out of heuyn. For the whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde to be had: any faythfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wold be glad to ſuffre any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:5373:17"/> of moſt cruell &amp; horryble payne or paſſyon (that is to ſay) ſurety of ſaluacyon.<note place="margin">Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctus Thoma. iiii. ſent. di. xv. q. .iii. ar. l.</note> For all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules beynge in payne ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely ſure, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of theyr ſaluacyon, that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr penaunce is paſte, and theyr ſynnes purged / they knowe for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente they ſhal go into heuen vnto euerlaſtynge ioy and comfort. But remembre that I ſayde / they ben communely ſure &amp; certayne of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon. For it may be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome one, or fewe ſoules haue nat that know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge / but that god (for ſome ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all offence / and for a ſpeciall payne &amp; punyſſhement therof) doth hyde, &amp; kepe that knowledge from them, as we haue in the reuelacyons of our holy mother ſaynte Byrget. And that payne is more alone, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the paynes of the other ſoules. For that ſure knowledge of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon,<note place="margin">Live. vi. c. xxxix. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> is vnto them a ſynguler con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in all paynes, and dothe cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:18"/> them to ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes with good wyll in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charyte of our lorde: glad to ſuffre moche more at his gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wyll and pleaſure. If thoſe that departe this lyfe, go ſtreyght vnto heuyn: than ben they ferre more happye that from the miſery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of this wretched worlde: they be come vnto the pleaſaunt poſſeſſion of ſo great vnſpekeable ioye. For you may be ſure it is an excellente ioye, to be there in companye with the pure virgynes, the holy confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours / the gloryous martyrs / di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne apoſtles, ſage patryarches / bryght ſhynynge aungels / and the virgyn mother our bleſſyd Lady, and all theſe to ſe and beholde with our reuerende lord, and ſouerayne ſauyour Ieſu Chryſt / And all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the preſence of the bleſſyd Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte / father ſon &amp; holy ghoſt, there prayenge all for vs, and lowly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſechinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hygh mageſte eterne, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5373:18"/> euerlaſting god. For al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd I thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke &amp; verely beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any faithful chriſtiane, wold be glad to expire &amp; ſuffre dethe euery day newely / if it were poſſible, &amp; oftimes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day, ſo he were ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he therby myght at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne &amp; come vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure / why tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (nowe I ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtomake) why for ſhame, ſhuld we as cowardes or chyldren fere &amp; drede deth? ſpecially ſith deth is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but like vnto a ſlepe. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old philoſophours ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſlepe was a very ymage of deth: &amp; as one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may knowe an other by his ymage althogh he had neuer ſe ne hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before:<note place="margin">ii. Mac. xii. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xi. Iob.</note> ſo may we know what deth is by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage, which is ſlepe: &amp; ſo is it called alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcripture i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places, &amp; our ſauiour him ſelfe ſaid: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lazarꝰ ſlept wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ded / &amp; deth alſo is called a ſhadow / but you ꝑceyue wel &amp; ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folkes be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat afrayde of a ſhadow, nor yet of ſtep nother. For oftimes we ſlepe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our
<pb facs="tcp:5373:19"/> feare or drede, and without any payne or grefe / but rather with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre and pleaſure / why ſhulde we than feare dethe ſyth we ſo euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e &amp; per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eyue by the ymage howe lytle dethe is to be drede / let vs therfore put awaye this opiny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onatyue feare and drede of dethe / and ſyth it dothe dayly approche &amp; wayte for vs: let vs agayne with glad mynde and redye good wyll, abyde and wayte for it, and haue therof a thurſt and a deſyre / rather than any feare or drede: howe be it (of a ſuretye) dethe is than leſt fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moſt deſyred: whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of the perſone / may (at the tyme of deth) be of ſure and vnfayned god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly frendes / conforted with the true teſtymonye and prayſe of vertue / wherfore (good deuoute chryſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) althoughe your reaſon &amp; ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge be nat ſufficyent to cauſe or to perſwade you / vtterly to diſpyſe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:19"/> deth / yet let your well ſpente lyfe &amp; clere conſcyence, perfourme and ſo ſatiſfie you that you be perſwaded: and verely beleue as a trothe euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and opyn vnto you / that to lyue lenger were more miſerye / &amp; that your lyfe hath be verey longe or rather ouerlonge. If it had plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed our lorde: before and erſte to haue called you. Thus now (good Chryſtianes) let vs without any care of deth, leaue the carnall mour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge, and waylynge therof / vnto our ſuruyuyng frendes / that with lamentacyon / and ſhal inteere and burye our bodyes. And let vs take an other maner of care and dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence / to prepare, apparell, and to order our ſelfe vnto that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knowe well, no perſone ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde nor eſcape / byleuynge and truſtyng verely, that he that made vs of nought / and whan we were loſt, wold ſo derely bye vs agayne / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:20"/> wyll nat ſuffre vs to dye. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as I ſayd before) to chaunge this wretched lyfe, for an other more precyous and ioyful / &amp; onely to be deſyred. All this hytherto ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I ſayde to the intente that you ſhulde exyle, exclude, and put away ferre from you, the commune feare full fantaſye of the odious opiny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deth / and ſomwhat to ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, and bylde in you a contrarye opinyon. A couetous deſyre to be with our lorde. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Nowe ſhall folowe the ſeconde parte of this interpryſe / of the dayly exercyſe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryence of deth.</head>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the exercyſe and experyence of dethe. The ſeconde parte of this interpryſe.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:20"/>
                     <p>FIrſt you muſt knowe, what is exercyſe / and what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perynce / &amp; howe by them you may come vnto the knowledge of deth. An exercyſe (than) is an acte dede &amp; an vſe of workynge or laborynge. Than done you exercyſe vertue,<note place="margin">Defini. of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> whan you put it vnto vſe and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng therof, &amp; the exercyſe of deth / is the acte and vſe of the workyng therof.<note place="margin">Defini. of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryence. i. Meth.</note> Experyence is a knowledge that without any maiſter or techer is founde out and gotyn, by exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe and vſe.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> And by many expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſayeth Ariſtotle arte / crafte or connynge is ingendred and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (as he ſayth) doth apꝑtayne &amp; by long proprely vnto ſingulare ꝑſones &amp; art craft or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng vnto al ꝑſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. And although that artcraft or connyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called ſpeculatyue may be had by lerning of a techer, or by dylygent ſtudye / yet this arte or craft that we ſpeke
<pb facs="tcp:5373:21"/> of here muſt nedely be had, by expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryence / and experyence, by exercyſe and vſe. So that yf you wyll haue the actyue knowledge of dethe / by the arte and crafte therof, you muſt begynne fyrſte at exercyſe and vſe. And yet can no man put a thynge vnto exercyſe / without ſome intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and leadynge therunto / other by techynge, ſtudye, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſicyon. you muſte than knowe fyrſt what the thing is that you ſhall put in exercyſe / and ſo to haue experyence, and knowledge therof (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) you muſt knowe what dethe is / or what is ment by this terme, or worde dethe. For the ſelfe terme deth dothe ſignifye / and is taken dyuerſly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyuers maners Somtyme dethe is taken, &amp; called a chaunge of lyfe. So the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune people done often vſe it, as whan they ſay of a deed perſon / he is nat deed (ſay they) out he hathe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:5373:21"/> his lyfe / and ſo dothe ſaynte Ambroſe ſay, as we ſhewed before.<note place="margin">De bono mortis.</note> And yet chaunge of lyfe is called deth in dyuers other maners. As whan a perſon dothe fall by ſynne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good lyfe vnto the ſtate of dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacyon or contrary / whan he doth aryſe by grace from ſynne vnto the ſtate of ſaluacyon.<note place="margin">Ro. vi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</note> Saynt Paule dothe ſhewe bothe vnto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes / as wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayeth that in our baptyſme we ben buryed with Chryſt vnto deth from ſynne / and we byleue we ſhall aryſe agayne with Chryſte vnto a newe lyfe of grace.<note place="margin">Rom. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> And for the tother parte he ſayeth, that occaſyon hathe decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the frayle perſon / and ſo hathe ſlayne hym, &amp; brought him to deth. This chaunge of life is,<note place="margin">Auguſti.</note> that ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dethe / that (as ſaynt Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne ſayeth) doth departe god from the ſoule. For god is the lyfe of the ſoule / &amp; whan god than is (by ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e)
<pb facs="tcp:5373:22"/> departed there from, the ſoule is deed. And this is the deth onely to be feared &amp; abhorred / as the worſte dethe of all dethes / and yet to ſaye trouthe, there is none other dethe euyll / except onely that dethe that muſt nedely folowe this deth / that is to ſay, the deth of both body and ſoule eterne and euerlaſtyng dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon. The other maner of dethe: that I ſpake of / that is: the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of euyll lyfe vnto good / <note place="margin">Rom. vl.</note> and of the whiche (as I ſayde) ſaynt Paule wrote vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes: is a good deth / whiche you and euery fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſone haue exercyſed and oft put in vſe, by reaſon of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. And whan nede ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyre, ben redy ſo to do / whan I ſpeke here of euyll lyfe to be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: I meane nat the ſtate onely of mortall or deedly ſynne. For many perſones, that ofte done vſe the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / done lyue without
<pb facs="tcp:5373:22"/> any deedly ſynne / but I meane the lyfe ſpotted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any vyce or ſynne.<note place="margin">Mercu. triſmeg.</note> For a great clerke ſayeth. Omne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mixtum eſt cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malo. Euery thinge good that is ours / &amp; doth appertayne vnto vs, is mixed or myngled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euyll. So that our whole lyfe, is euer mixed, coupled, &amp; cumbred with ſome viſe &amp; euyll / which natwithſtandynge may (by the grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes) be day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purged, and ſo our life chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged / and we therby haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exercyſe, vſe, &amp; experyence of this deth. But yet is there an other maner of deth cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led of lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, meditatio mortis / that is to meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meditacion (that is to ſaye) the cogytacyon, thought and remembraunce / the buſynes, tractacyon or intreatye, mencyon, &amp; diſputacyon of dethe. Tota vita philoſophorum, meditatio mortis eſt. All the whole lyfe of philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: and wyſe men (ſaye they) is
<pb facs="tcp:5373:23"/> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentacyon, remembraunce, &amp; mencyon or diſputacyon of deth / oft mencyon, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce / oft diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacyon, and diſcuſſyon of any thyng doth cauſe it to be the better knowen.<note place="margin">Cicero. Macer. libro. i. de ſomno Sipio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is. Eraſ. in Enchr.</note> And men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely wyll make oft mencion, ſpeke, and talke often of that thyng wherunto they haue deſyre, loue, or haue good mynde and affection. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye they wyl nat here tell of that thyng that they hate, and loue nat: and ſo is it of many perſones that wyll nat here ſpeke, ne any mencyon made of deth. And yf (by chaunce) any mencyon be made of dethe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne theyr myndes and wylles / they wyll lyfte vp the hande and bleſſe them, or els murmure out ſoftly: ſome ſuperſticyous prayers as though they harde ſpeke of the deuyll / or of ſome abhomynable &amp; cruell dede. And certaynly it is no meruayle thoughe ſuche perſones
<pb facs="tcp:5373:23"/> be affrayde to dye, and lothe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto / becauſe they be nat acquoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with deth, nor be exercyſed ther in. But as (in caſe) a perſon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> longe tyme had layne fetred in pryſone / coulde nat for lacke of exercyſe go faſte, ne renne whan he were newly put vnto lyberte / ſo theſe maner of perſones, wrapped in the worlde / &amp; fetred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe / can nat quycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and couragyouſlye for lacke of experyence: walke the way of deth, whiche natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng they muſt nedely trede / &amp; paſſe whether they wyll or no. Lacke (I ſay) of exercyſe vſe, and experyence / cauſeth theſe perſones to feare and drede dethe. As by example, chyldren and ſome women, or ſuch ꝑſones neuer had experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ne knowledge of a bugge that is a perſonage, that in playe dothe repreſent the deuyll at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt ſyght / ben moche affrayde therof: in ſo moche that ſome ꝑſones haue
<pb facs="tcp:5373:24"/> ben in ieoꝑdye to loſe theyr wytte &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therby. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward haue knowledge what it was &amp; by vſe haue experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof: they ben than nothyng affrayde therof, but rather done take pleaſure ther in. So is it of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue nat the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of deth / bycauſe they will nat take, but rather wyll they fle / &amp; auoyde / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe &amp; exerciſe therof. But &amp; yf they knewe what / &amp; how great profet there is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exercyſe / medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon &amp; oft recorde: &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of dethe: they wolde nat fle nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde it: but rather with ſtudye &amp; diligence gyue &amp; applye them ſelfe dayly therunto.<note place="margin">Ec. i. d. Pſalmꝰ. xxxviii.</note> The wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith. Fili memorare nouiſſima tua. &amp;c. In al thy werkes ſone (ſayth he) re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membre thy laſte ende / and thou ſhalte neuer offende god. The prophete therfore prayde vnto our lorde ſayenge. Notum fac mihi domine finem meum. Good lorde
<pb facs="tcp:5373:24"/> (ſayeth he) let me haue knowledge of my laſt ende, as though he ſayd. Good lorde gyue me grace that (by the dayly exercyſe, and meditacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of deth) I may haue an experyence and knowledge of my laſt ende: &amp; euermore to be redy therunto / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng vnto thy wyll &amp; pleaſure. Nothyng is more valyaunt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and put awaye ſynne from the ſoule: nor yet more profytable to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plenyſſh &amp; garnyſſhe the ſoule with good vertues: then is the dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe, &amp; meditacyon of dethe. But howe to put &amp; apply them ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that exercyſe, all ꝑſones can nat tell. For many that fayne wolde haue and vſe the meditacyon and exercyſe of deth: haue nat the way, ne knowe any fourme or faſſyon therof. And yet ben there dyuers fourmes and wayes therof and all good. For ſome perſones:<note place="margin">One ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe of dethe. Tho.</note> done go no forther, but to remembre
<pb facs="tcp:5373:25"/> and thynke that deth is the payne of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e inflycted, iudged &amp; appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by almyghtye god, vnto our fyrſt parentes: and therfore due &amp; ryght vnto all theyr poſteryte, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and of ſprynge: ſo that no man after them dyd euer eſcape deth / ne neuer man ſhall, vnto the day of generall iudgement: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſure it is that we muſt dye: but whan or howe we can nat tell. To haue therfore a dayly exercyſe of deth. I ſhall ſet you here .ii. four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of this exercyſe.<note place="margin">An other fourme or maner of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe of dethe.</note> The fyrſte fourme is this that in ſome conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyent tyme of the day or nyght ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted and choſen for this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe: you ſhall ymagyne, call vnto remembraunce and ſo ſet forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes &amp; ſyght of your ſoule: howe you haue ſene or herde of a perſon that hathe ben condemned by iudgement, vnto bodely dethe: as to be brent, hanged, or heded, or
<pb facs="tcp:5373:25"/> ſuche other. Than ſaye or thynke vnto your ſelfe: what and if I were in ſuche caſe: as that perſon was I knowe well, and knowledge vnto our lorde: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue deſerued more cruel dethe (for euery deedly ſynne, is worthy more payne / than any worldly payne) or els yf you were in ſuche caſe as you haue dremed in your ſlepe, or herde of dremyng / that you ſhulde forthwith go vnto the execucyon of deth, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye: howe than wolde I do / or howe ſhulde I then, or were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to do for the ſaluacion of my ſoule / or yf euer you haue ſene or herde of the maner of them that ben nere vnto theyr paſſage / &amp; lye drawyng vpon vnto deth. And the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome wepynge &amp; mournyng / ſome cryenge, and callynge vpon the ſycke / to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre our lorde god and our moſte ſwete ſauyour Ieſu Chriſt / our bleſſyd lady with other
<pb facs="tcp:5373:26"/> holy ſayntes. And remembre howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſycke is than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred with ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and payne: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can do lytle for hym ſelfe / all weke, feble, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. And howe than, the ghoſtly enemye the deuyll wolde preſe: and come in before you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a foule ſorte of vgſum ſouldiours / &amp; aſſayle you in many ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry wyſe / lay before you the multytude of your ſynnes &amp; all your omyſſyons of ſuche good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as you might haue done / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of you were neglygent, and all to brynge you vnto diſpeyre of your ſaluacyon: &amp; that you ſhulde leaue your faythe / and haue no hope ne truſt of mercy. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort it ſhulde be vnto you at that tyme / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had prepared &amp; made redy before hande for all theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / &amp; howe oftymes you had ſene in your ſoule all this concluſyon: &amp; howe often you had reaſynge vp your frayle hert diſpyſed deth and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:26"/> nothyng ſet therby / &amp; how you had apointed / to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth is none euyll but great good / and that you tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld make an ende of al myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; ſhortly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnto a better ſtate. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begyn to ſay vnto your ſelfe. I wil now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> helth ſtudy, &amp; exerciſe my ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this fourme: &amp; ſpecially how I ſhal anſwere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lothly beſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. I wyl now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this tyme <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of deth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nedely ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / left vp my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; hert vnto my lord / &amp; beſech him of grace &amp; ſuccour / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil I beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good bleſſed lady mother of mercy: my good angel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my holy patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s there namyng ſuch ſaintes as you haue in moſt ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler deuocyon: &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſayntes of heuen, to be there <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent with me to ayde, confort, &amp; to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cruel beſt. And as vnto my ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es ſay you I haue gadred them al togeder (as ferre as I can reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre) &amp; brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlon there to be polyſſhed, rubbed, &amp; ſcoured
<pb facs="tcp:5373:27"/> (that ſtone is the holy ſacrament of penaunce) that by the merytes of Chryſtes precyous blode / hathe waſſhed awaye my ſynne. For I knowe well that one drope alone of that moſt holy ſacred blod, were ſufficyent, and ynoughe / and ferre more than ynoughe / to waſſhe and clenſe all the ſynne of the worlde / and yet ſhed he all his blode euery drope. And therfore (nowe at this tyme for and in ſtede of that tyme: I put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precyous blode with his bytter paſſyon and his moſt cruel / and ſhamefull deth / bytwene me &amp; all the ſynnes that euer I dyd in thought, worde, or dede, &amp; betwexe me and his wrath and diſpleaſure. And hauynge full fayth and truſt vnto his promyſe (that is) that he wyll gracyouſly receyue all peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes vnto mercy: I now for then boldly prouoke the and deffye the moſt cruell and falſe fende, and I
<pb facs="tcp:5373:27"/> ſtraytely charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in his holy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed name Ieſu: that if you haue any thinge to lay vnto my charge: ſhewe it nowe: tell it out. For thou ſhalt nother confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, ne feare me / nor yet diſconforde me therwith / but rather do me great pleaſure to put me in remembraunce.</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> If I haue forgoten to confeſſe any thynge worthy penaunce / that I may nowe (vnto thy confuſyon / ſhewe it and with the wyll at the leſt) &amp; deſyre of perfect contricyon, and with indignacyon: I may caſt it at thy face amonge all the other ſynnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I dyd by any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / whiche ſynnes I vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, as nothynge appertaynynge vnto me. For I am gracyouſly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, waſſhed, and clenſed in the precyous blode of my ſouerayne ſauyour Ieſu Chryſt. And therfore I bequethe and commytte all my ſynne, vnto the cruell beſt / the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb facs="tcp:5373:28"/> &amp; begynner of all ſynne: with the to remayne from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s it came and whether it ſhall / in the &amp; with the eternally to be punyſſhed. And than leauyng him there: turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our lorde god, &amp; vnto our ſwete ſauyour Ieſu. And as yf you were than, at the poynt of deth / axe hym hertely forgyuenes of all your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes / and beſeche his goodnes of mercy and grace, &amp; pray y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes (as I ſayd before) to pray for you, and than (yf you be goynge vnto reſt, whiche tyme is moſt conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yent for this exerciſe) bleſſe you thus In manus tuas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendo ſpiritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum: redemiſti me domine deus veritatis. In nomine patris &amp; filii, &amp; ſpiritus ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cti. Amen. Makynge a croſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a holy candell yf you haue it preſent, after the maner that you haue / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your boke for houſholders. And thus do .iii. tymes together / and ſo go vnto reſte as you ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:5373:28"/> go vnto your grace. This exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe (good deuout ſoules) is nat to be diſpyſed / for by dayly vſe and cuſtome / it ſhall inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre and bylde in you a great boldnes, and hardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. So that whan ſo euer natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dethe ſhall approche / you ſhall than, nat as a woman or chyld, but as a very man / as a ſtronge and myghty champyon thus ſurely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med / ſtande ſtyfly without feare, or drede, and lytle care / or rather ſet nought by deth / but vtterly diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dethe, as euery houre and tyme redy therunto.<note place="margin">An other exercyſe of dethe.</note> But nowe we ſhall lede you forth vnto an other exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe of dethe more hygh &amp; excellent tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this / &amp; ſo to haue experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deth / that more proprely is called dethe / wherby you ſhall nat onely without fere or drede) diſpyſe deth, but alſo (as an hongrye ꝑſon) you ſhall haue an auidiouſe &amp; gredye appetite to thurſt &amp; wyſſh for deth.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:29"/> And with a feruent mynde, and fla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge deſyre / you ſhall langour mourne and longe for deth. Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge with ſaynt Paule.<note place="margin">Phi. i. c</note> Cupio diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolui et eſſe cum Chriſto. I couete wyſſhe, &amp; wyll, to be diſſolued from this preſente lyfe, and to be with Chryſt. In this exercyſe: you ſhall nat onely haue the experience / and the full arte, ſcyence, connyng, and knowledge of dethe / but alſo the very practyſe of dethe / ſo that you ſhall euery day (whan you wyll) be as verely deed / accordynge vnto the very definicyon of dethe. For deth (after all auctours) proprely taken is.<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion of dethe.</note> A departynge in ſondre / of the ſoule and the bodye. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte than the ſoule from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body: and to rendre and put eyther vnto his propre and naturall place / is the very practyſe of deth. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre and naturall place or whome of the ſoule, is heuyn. Wherof ſaint
<pb facs="tcp:5373:29"/> Paule ſayth.<note place="margin">Heb. xiii. c.</note> Non habemus hic ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatem manentem, ſed aliam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirimus: we haue here (ſayeth he) no dwellyng place / but we do ſeke and ſerche for an other place.<note place="margin">Gen. iii. c</note> And the naturall place of the body, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth / for thens it came, and thyder it muſte agayne / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer than the ſoule (by dilygent ſtudy) is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed wholly in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thynges / and the body lefte without the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or wyttes / that is without hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, ſeynge, ſmellynge, taſtynge, and touchyng / than is that perſon as deed. But that a perſon (for the ſtate of this lyfe) may be in ſuche caſe / the philoſophours done ſhew &amp; determyne. Tullie ſayeth.<note place="margin">Plato. &amp; Cicero in tuſc. i. queſt.</note> Fieri poteſt, vt oculis, et auribus aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: nihil videamus ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> audiamꝰ. It may come to paſſe (ſayeth he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoughe our eyes &amp; eares be opyn: yet ſhall we nother ſe, nor here. Many a holy perſon (as ſaynt) Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine
<pb facs="tcp:5373:30"/> of Sene and dyuers other) hath ben ſo depe in contemplacion that the body (for the tyme) was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out the ſenſes, ſo that whan they were prycked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pynnes, or nedles, they nothynge felte. So than this exercyſe, ſtandeth al in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, which thing who dayly vſeth ſhall be ſo experte, and practyſed in deth / that whan ſo euer it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche and come, it ſhall be no new thyng vnto the ꝑſon. For betwyxt naturall deth, and this deth of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templacyon, is lytle difference. For as the perſon that exſpireth and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parteth this lyfe / dothe leaue and forſake all this worlde, and all the care of kynne or frendes / as father mother, ſyſter, and brother, neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure / &amp; the whole pleaſure of all. So doth the perſon, that is deed in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacyon for that tyme / leaue the body as a lumpe of claye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mynde, care, or thoughte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:30"/> therupon / or vpon any other bode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or worldly thyng / wherfore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dethe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth (as I ſayd before) it ſhall nother be newe, nor ſtraunge vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon that hath ben dayly exerciſed therin / &amp; that had ſo large experyence therof, and often prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed the ſame. But as you haue herde of .ii. marouwſe that (for tyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of theyr lande) done laboure ſore all day together, and at nyght theyr labours fyniſhed and ended / done thankefully, and gladly eche departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other vnto theyr owne whomes, howſes, or dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſo doubtles done the body and the ſoule, whan theyr labours ben accomplyſſhed and at an ende / and the due tyme commen / they done gladly and ioyfully departe, eche vnto his propre whome / the body vnto his naturall place the erthe. And the ſoule as a priſoner newly loſed and put vnto lyberte / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:31"/> doth ren ſtreyght forth hyr redye race / hyr knowen cours / hyr tryed and ofte troden path, and her well vſed way vnto her propre and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall place / that is heuyn. But here nowe you wyll axe of me / in what maner of contemplacion you may beſt put this deth in exercyſe / and ſo to haue the ſaid experyence / and practyſe of dethe, wherunto I anſwere that (althoughe you can teche me that leſſon better than I you) I wyll ſende you vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lytle werke that I deuyſed vnto youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon, or howſelynge. For to wryte and ſetforth all that here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, ſhuld be ſuperfluous. Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally ſyth this werke is ſo lytle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may (with ſmall coſte) ioyne or bynde it with that werke. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue I cauſed it to be prynted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame volume. And yet becauſe you ſhal nat fynde the ende of this lytle werke all naked and bare / we
<pb facs="tcp:5373:31"/> ſhall make you a breue and ſhorte remembraunce of theſe thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ben ſayd in effecte, althoughe nat after that ſame ordre.<note place="margin">The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this deth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placion</note> Fyrſt tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purpoſynge at that tyme to haue the very experyence, and practyſe of deth / reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre depely from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s you came. For you were nat, ne be of your ſelfe. Than remembre that whan you had a beynge / what you were / a filthy lumpe of ſlymy erth / and yet agayne, whan that ſlymye clay was fourmed and framed vp with your ſoule / and you a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creature / &amp; therunto a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture moſt noble except aungell / yet were you but an hethen hounde / vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme you receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of baptiſme. Than reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre whan, where, howe, and of whom / and by whome you had all that you nowe haue &amp; all that you euer ſhall haue that is or ſhall be good / and you ſhal fynde (by reaſon) and perceyue
<pb facs="tcp:5373:32"/> that you hadde neuer / ne haue, or ſhall haue any thynge of your ſelfe but euyll. For whan you were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, you had a begynnynge in your mothers wombe / and that by ſynfull generacyon with ful fylthy and lotheſum mater / thus you ſe whan, where, and howe (that is) wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you were nat, you had beyng: where? in your mothers wombe / howe by ſynfull concepcyon. Of whome tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had you al, of our lorde god alone. And by whome, &amp; what meane? Certenly by the meane of our lorde &amp; ſauyour Ieſu Chryſte, the ſeconde perſon in Trinite very eſſencyall god one / and the ſame ſelfe ſubſtaunce, and nature with the father, and the holy ghoſt. Se well, beholde, and conſydre who it is that hathe done for you: howe excellent the perſon is. And than for whom he dyd. For you of whom he had no nede / nor you any thyng
<pb facs="tcp:5373:32"/> had or coulde or might do for him / but all he dyd for loue, and of mere charyte / and that alſo for his enemye / and ſo beynge in depe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, neuer to be delyuerde, but by hym alone. Nowe conſyder, and pondre well who this perſone is / and than loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelf make collacyon / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare both together, although there may in deed, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryſon be made. yet ſe, &amp; beholde howe great &amp; mighty a ꝑſon he is / how lytle, &amp; howe infyrme &amp; feble a ꝑſon you be, howe wyſe, &amp; how well lerned he is / &amp; howe lytle lernynge &amp; wyſdome you haue, how ryche he is: &amp; howe poore you ben / howe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; noble he is, &amp; how ruſtycall a vyllayne you be / howe goodly a ꝑſon he is, and howe vyle &amp; fylthy you be: how kynde &amp; louyng he is: &amp; howe churlyſſhe, &amp; frowarde you be. And to conclude, he moſt hyghe god / and you a wretched worme
<pb facs="tcp:5373:33"/> of the earthe he all: and you ryght nought. After this collacto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng what maner of ꝑſones bothe ben: than pondre and wey, what &amp; howe moche he dyd for you. Fyrſt he left (in maner) all heuyn for you: and here toke vpon hym your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / &amp; ſo made you a great eſtate / coſyn and of kynne vnto almighty god. And yet dyd he ſerue here for you: nat onely .vii. yeres: as Iacob for Rachell: but for a worſe &amp; more lothſum than Lia, all the dayes of his lyfe / and here begyn to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre that lyfe of our ſauyour. After ſome ſuche auctours as we haue named in the other workes / or at the leaſt vnder ſuche a ſhorte fourme as we haue ſet forth in the boke of houſholders. Thus his bleſſyd incarnacyon, his ioyfull byrthe / his paynefull circumſicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: his honorable epiphanye / his legall preſentacyon / his ſorowfull
<pb facs="tcp:5373:33"/> flyght into Egypt / his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable retourne and commynge agayne in to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey / his meruaylous and lerned diſputyng with the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours at .xii. yeres of age, his lowly obedyence vnto his parentes, his educacyon &amp; bryngynge vp vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of nere .xxx. yeres his baptiſme his faſt in wyldernes / his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon there of the wycked ſpiryte &amp; his victory. The callynge eletcyon and choſynge of his apoſtles and diſcyples, prechynge, techynge, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and miracles / &amp; his manye wrongfull repreues, rebukes / and infamyes of the iewes, and theyr malicyous awaytes / his ſolempe ſoper / his moſt meke minyſtrye / &amp; ſeruyce in the waſſhynge of the fete of his apoſtles. The worthy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracyon of his bleſſyd body &amp; blode in the whiche ſacrament, all his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were made preeſtes / &amp; had the ſame power, his moſt ſwete ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:5373:34"/> &amp; his tediouſe agonye / whan he ſwette water and blode / his fals betrayenge (by Iudas) and his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge his preſentacyon vnto the byſſhoppes Annas and Cayphas. And the cruell dealyng of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ues &amp; the preſentynge of hym (by them) vnto Pylate, &amp; by hym vnto He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode by whom mocked and clothed in a whyte fooles cote / he was ſende agayne vnto Pylate and by hym examyned, and without cauſe founde: put naked and ſcourged &amp; arayde with a purpure garment &amp; crowned with thornes with a rede in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de as a ſceptre al i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age &amp; ſcorne brought forthe before the iewes &amp; by their crye, &amp; requeſt: put agayne into his owne clothes &amp; condemned vnto deth his payne full beryng of the heuy croſſe / his fatigacyon / and feyntynge vnder the ſame, ſo that he fell vnto the grounde / his crucifixon &amp; naylyng
<pb facs="tcp:5373:34"/> vpon the croſſe &amp; his pytefull han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vpon the ſame his deth with a lowde crye. The woundynge of his hert after that deth his takyng downe, &amp; buryall, his gloryous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection &amp; apperynges / his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous aſcencyon into heuyn / where he toke for you poſſeſſyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plate: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was prepared &amp; ordayned for you, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Here you may remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place: whiche in hit ſelfe is moſte hyghly beauteous, fayre, goodly, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte aboue that can be thoughte vpon erthe and of all thynges that ben in this worlde, is there plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and aboundance without any nede or wante poſſeſſyon is there of the lande that neuer ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye / &amp; ryches that neuer ſhall be miniſſhed or made leſſe. And as vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modites of the body &amp; goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of nature there is youth, euer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:35"/> floryſſhyng freſſhe without age or any miſeryes therof. Beaute and fayrenes, without any deformyte / or fadynge. Myght and ſtrength<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without debilyte or feblenes helth without ſyckenes, or diſeaſe / all pleaſure and neuer payne. Euer myrth without any mornyng, euer gladnes: and neuer ſadnes. Euer ioy, and neuer ſorowe of all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentacion without any mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure or grudge. Euer loue, and neuer hate. Euer charyte, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enuye, mercye, pitye, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon / without any crueltye, or vnkyndnes. Euer vnyte and peace and neuer varyaunce: ne debate. Euer trouth and fidelite: without any falſhed or deceyte. Euer iuſtice equite: and ryghte / and neuer op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion / ne wronge. Euer due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure / and reuerence &amp; neuer dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne ne dyſpyte. And to conclude there is al that is good / and neuer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:35"/> euyll. And of all theſe thynges: conſtant durans,<note place="margin">1. Cor. ii.</note> without any my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhynge, mutabilyte or chaung. And yet ben there mo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eare may here, eye may ſe, to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge may tell, or any herte may thynke. whiche almyghty god hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for them that loue hym. And yet there is vnto all theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, lyfe immortall, &amp; euerlaſtyng. And yet forthermore, you may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydre in what company / and with whom you ſhall vſe, and inioye the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytes. There ſhall you fynde your holy patrones / ſuche ſayntes, as you dayly haue ſerued / the pure company of virgynes / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours, and martyrs / the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, the apoſtles / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patryarches &amp; prophetes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodly bright company of angels / al redy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you vnto our lady the bleſſyd gloryous virgyne Marye / and by her with them to be recommended
<pb facs="tcp:5373:36"/> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto her dere ſone our lorde / &amp; moſte ſwete ſauyour Ieſu, which wyl nat diſdayne to receyue you moſt beningly &amp; gently &amp; ſo to re<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; offre you vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his moſt worthy father which (by him) is alſo your father. Se now (good deuout ſoule) beholde, &amp; loke wel &amp; inwardly, ꝑceyue where you nowe ben / &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whom. With your lorde &amp; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ter / your very father &amp; brother your gouernor &amp; gyder / your helpe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your only refuge, &amp; ſuccour your inward loue: your whole hert &amp; deſyre, redemer &amp; ſauyour, your creature &amp; maker, your god &amp; all your good: with all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſayntes &amp; angels of heuyn in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryous trinite, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone &amp; the holy ghoſt .iii. diſtinct ꝑſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; one nature one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce one eſſencyall god. Se nowe (I ſaye) and take hede where and with whome you be. And here kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge
<pb facs="tcp:5373:36"/> or rather lyenge downe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your face: remayne, byde &amp; dwell here ſtyll / here expyre &amp; dye ſtarke deed / &amp; vtterly that no ſoule ne ſpiryte be lefte or byde in youre body / but all for the tyme ſo ferre departed / nat onely from all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the world, but alſo from the ſelfe body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there lyenge as a lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe of cley be lefte without any ſenſes or wyttes of heryng, ſeynge, ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, taſtyng, or touchynges. So done we rede (as I ſayde before) of ſaynt Ambroſe,<note place="margin">Aug. li. confeſ.</note> ſaynt Kathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yne of Shene with diuers other. This is nowe the mooſt hyghe poynte of this exercyſe and practyſe of dethe after the verye definicyon of deth. Whiche (as I ſade) is called a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partynge of the ſoule from the bodye. For in this dethe (for that tyme) youre ſoule is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from youre body, ſo that you be nat than youre ſelfe: but deed
<pb facs="tcp:5373:37"/> &amp; clene fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelfe. For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yren lyenge in the fyre / is by ſimilytude al fyre, ſo ben you al one with god. Qui adheret deo / vnus ſpiritꝰ eſt.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vi.d.</note> Who ſo euer (ſayeth ſaynt Paule) dothe cleue, and ſtycke faſte vnto our lorde: is with hym one ſpiryte. So ben you than that ſame thyng that you ſhall be / with our lorde hereafter, that is al one with hym / dwellynge and abydynge in hym, and he in you ſo al diuyne &amp; godly. Say nowe (good deuout ſoule) yf you can thynke or ſuppoſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ce, that any faythfull chriſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ſynge this exerciſe: and ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ge ſo large experyence &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe of deth / may haue, fele, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yue, any notable payne in dethe / ſyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> nowe in this deth, ſo oftymes exercyſed the bodye prycked with pynnes or nedyles: feleth no payne at all. Or howe may any horrour drede, or feare, troble or moue that
<pb facs="tcp:5373:37"/> perſon / that is in ſuche place, with ſuche company and in ſuch caſe as before we haue ſhewed. yet (ſaye you) ſyr the deuyll wyll be preſent at my dethe / what than? ſaye I ſo peraduenture / he wyll be at this dayly exercyſe. For ſo done we rede in the lyues: and collacyons of the holy fathers / but that hathe alway ben, and euer ſhall be vnto his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſyon / rebuke, and hurte / and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your triumphe, glorye, &amp; prayſe. But yet you ſaye, that the ſyght of that greſlye ghoſt, can nat be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great feare: wherunto I ſaye agayne that although the ſyght of hym be (of it ſelfe) horryble, vgly, &amp; fearefull / yet ben there dyuers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes redy at hande to helpe. One is that may be ſure, he can nat hurt you. An other is,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diue Brigit. li. vi. ca. lxxxxiii.</note> the preſence of the holy ſayntes, your ſayde fryndes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll reſtrayne his power and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licyous wyll. For they ben moche
<pb facs="tcp:5373:38"/> more valeant and myghty than he is. And doubt you nat they wyll al be preſte, and redy there at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme about you / nat feyned, but as faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full frendes, with whome well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoynted and fully knowen / you ben nowe and of longe tyme haue ben very familyer and whomely. Truſte you ſurely in them, for they wyll nat deceyue you. For yf they dyd, they were nat faithful / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feyned frendes. For a very frende (ſayth the wyſeman) loueth at all tymes and euer is proued in neceſſyte or nede: &amp; at dethe is moſt nede. For although good loue and faythfull fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhyppe / be well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in all the lyfe tyme: yet is it better proued at the tyme of dethe / and beſt of all after deth. For than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely feyned fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des done ſone forget. But theſe frendes wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forget you. For as they nowe (in your helth) done dayly conforte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:38"/> and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you in all temtacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: ſo wyl they at your deth delyuer you out of all daungers / &amp; afterwarde wyl they deduce, lede, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey, &amp; cary or bere you vp vnto the place &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany before reherſed. And yet haue you no meruayle though (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne tyme) they ſuffre you to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled &amp; grudged with the opinyon of dethe &amp; with the drede of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vgly ſyght. For they done ſo ſuffre for your welth &amp; meryte that you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may be exerciſed with deth: and ſo to be euer redy for it. For dethe only ſemeth euyll and onely is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by opinyon &amp; nat of any other ryght cauſe. For deth of it ſelfe is very good &amp; to be loked &amp; wayted for, &amp; receyued of all ꝑſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſpecially thus exercyſed / nat onely without feare or drede of payne / but alſo, as we ſayd before, with feruent deſyre great ioy &amp; gladnes as the fynall concluſyon and laſte ende of all
<pb facs="tcp:5373:39"/> miſeryes, ſorowes, and all euyls, &amp; as the begynnynge of all welthe &amp; goodnes (that is to ſaye) of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge helthe and ſaluacyon in the blyſſe of heuyn. Whyther he brynge vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bought vs, our lorde &amp; moſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu Chryſt, that lyueth and reigneth with god the father / and with god the holy ghoſt world without ende. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Thus (after our poore abilyte) haue made an ende of this poore labour of the dayly exercyſe, experyence and practyſe of dethe. *</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han I had wrytten vp this lytle werke redye to the pryntyng / it pleaſed a wyſe and well lerned man, to take the laboure to rede it ouer, and to ſhewe his iudgement and mynde in dyuers thinges and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:39"/> places. And amonge other, becauſe I had made mencyon in it / of rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es or tranſes (vnto the whyche in dede) very fewe ꝑſons done duely attayne or clymbe, &amp; come ſo hye / he aduyſed me to warne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuoute reders therof / that they gyue nat to lyght credence to all ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones. For many of them haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued manye men, that were full holy and deuoute. For thoſe may ſoneſt be deceyued in ſuch perſons, becauſe they euer ſuppoſe the beſte in euery perſone, without ſuſpicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euyll in any perſon. And they ben mooſt glad to here y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde ſhulde ſo viſyte and comforte hys people. But yet ſuch perſones may alſo in them ſelfe be diſceyued dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly. For ſome ſuch perſons that were ſimple and very deuout, haue ben diſceyued by a wycked ſpiryte / that (to illude and mocke them / hath tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfygured and ſhewed hym
<pb facs="tcp:5373:40"/> ſelfe as an angel of lyght / and hath ſhewed vnto the perſones many thynges full good and godly / and ſome thinges to come after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of prophecy, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue truely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to paſſe in effecte: and all to cauſe them to gyue faythe and credence vnto other thynges vnlaufull and falſe. But to wryte here, howe ſuch a ſpiryte ſhulde be knowen from an angel or a good ſpiryte: it ſhuld be a longe werke, and alſo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluus, ſyth, who ſo euer haue myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to ſe that matter / may haue it well and playnly ſetforth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in englyſſhe, by a lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a bacheler of diuinyte / one of our deuout bretherne, lately departed: whome Ieſu ꝑdon, mayſter Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Bonde / in his boke called the Pylgremage of perfeccyon in the .vii. chapyter of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de boke and in the thyrde and .iiii. chapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the thyrde boke, in the .iii.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:40"/> dayes iourney. Some other ꝑſons ben deceyued onely by the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of fantaſye, whiche cauſeth them to thynke and beleue verely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche thynges as (by onely yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynacyon) come vnto theyr myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ben verely ſpoken vnto them / as ſome done thynke that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowe or other byrde, dothe ſaye or ſynge certayne wordes, or that the bell or bellys done rynge and ſaye after theyr ymagynacyon. And of this ſorte ben many perſones, &amp; moche different, accordynge to the diſeaſe of the hede / as the fantaſye is more or leſſe corrupted. And yet ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll ſhewe many meruaylous thynges, that they beleue verely for true, which in dede were neuer true. But theſe perſones done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munelye ſhewe nothynge that is greatly euyll: nor yet any greate good / but that men may fone diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne and perceyue for fantaſyes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5373:41"/> ymagynacyon / except the perſones were ſome preuey ſynners. And than wyl the wycked ſperyte be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to put hym ſelfe in preaſe / and with that corrupcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to helpe forth vnto illuſyon. But yet ben other deceyuers, thoughe none of this ſorte / but of a more deueliſſhe ſorte very ypocrytes, that feyne them ſelfe to haue reuelacyons, &amp; knowe well they haue none ſuche, but that (to deceyue the people) ſeme in a tranſe or rapt / whan they wyll, as we rede of Dauid, that feyned him ſelfe madde,<note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eg. xxi.d.</note> and in a rage vpon a certayne tyme: For a good purpoſe to ſaue his ſelfe. And ſo playde his pagyant, that he frothed or fomed at the mouthe / &amp; raged as though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he had ben furyous and madde in dede. And ſo done theſe wretches the diſceyuynge of many perſones wilfully and of purpoſe. But howe to be ware of ſuche wretches and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:41"/> ypocrytes: ſurely it is very harde. For as to gyue ouerlyght credence to ſuche perſones, is agaynſt wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: ſo vtterly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to diſpyſe them / is peryllous &amp; agaynſte vertue. Wyſdome is therfore, to proue well the ſpiryte before. yet do I nowe ymagyn what many perſons wyll ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that is, that this exercyſe is a mater ouer hyghe / and excedynge the wyttes and vnderſtandyng of ſymple vnlerned people. And ſo is the tother worke alſo / wherunto I do ſende them in this worke, that is to ſay / the diſpoſicyon and ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce vnto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minyon or houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge. Wherunto I ſaye agayne, that bothe the workes ben ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded into ſuch partes: that euery perſon may take what he wyll, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to his ſtate and condicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Rede the werke ones ouer, and than choſe / for I thynke there ben
<pb facs="tcp:5373:42"/> but fewe perſones: but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they may lyghtly vnderſtande and vſe one of thoſe exercyſes. And (as a great lerned man ſayd of a werke that he had ſende forthe) althoughe this werke were ſo deuyſed:<note place="margin">Cicero de orato ꝓfecto.</note> that fewe perſones myght attayne to the full heyght and clere vnderſtandynge therof: yet ſhulde no perſon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre, ne be diſcouraged thereby. For as a prycke or marke is ſet in a butte for all men to ſhute at: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe none hytte the prycke. Thoſe that done ſhute nere ben nat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out prayſe.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ix. d.</note> And ſaynt Paule ſayeth, whan there is a glayue ſet vp for renners: all or many done renne / but one catcheth the glayue alone / and yet is it nother ſhame ne rebuke, to wynne the ſeconde or the thyrde game. But here in our ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe, none that dothe aſſaye to renne / ſhalbe without a ſynglar rewarde.<note place="margin">1. Cor. iii.c.</note> For (as the ſame apoſtle ſayeth)
<pb facs="tcp:5373:42"/> euery perſon ſhall receyue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre wages or rewarde: acccordyng to his labour and deſeruynge. And many tymes it may here fortune, and come to paſſe / that thoſe that come laſte: ſhal be fyrſt and beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.<note place="margin">Math. xx. b.</note> So ſayeth our ſauyour in the goſpell. Erunt primi nouiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, et nouiſſimi primi. In this campe / the fyrſt ſhalbe laſt, and the laſt ſhall (in rewarde) be fyrſt. The reſpect and weyght of this labour: ſtandeth nat in the bodely exercyſe of the outwarde werke / but in the infors and dilygence of the wyll / put therunto your good wyll and dilygence to do what you can: And thoughe it be but very very lytle that you ſpede or do in this exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: that lytle lytle, thoughe it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo lytle: yet ſhall it be greatly rewarded. And peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, moch more meryte and rewarde ſhall the dull perſone haue by that infors,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:43"/> dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and good wyll: than ſhall the lerned and quycke wytted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: that more lyghtly and with leſſe labour done ſpede in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Let no perſon therfore diſpayre ne take diſcomforte with any dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For the poete ſayeth. Labor improbus omnia vincit. Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune labour doth ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And yet though ſome perſons can (by no meanes, fall vnto the hygheſt exerciſe of this leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fall vnto prayer / and be ſory that they can nat flye ſo hygh, makyng proteſtacyon / and call our lorde to wytneſſe / that fayne &amp; gladly they wolde do what beſte myght pleaſe his goodnes / And let them there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte, recommende, betake, and bequeth them ſelfe body and ſoule vnto his handes at that tyme: as they intende to do, at the houre of dethe. And beſeche his grace / that this recommendacyon &amp; bequeſte,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:43"/> may ſtande / and of hym be recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for that tyme / and therwith let them ſaye. In manns tuas. &amp;c. as is beforeſayd. Some ꝑſones euery yere ones at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, and ſome .iiii. tymes, that euery quarter ones / done make theyr funeralles / that is / all the ſolempnyte of theyr bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryalles, with Dirige and maſſe / &amp; offre theyr maſſe peny them ſelfe. And after that / make a feaſt &amp; dele almes: as thoughe they were than deed in dede &amp; buryed / alſo whiche cuſtome I prayſe very moch. And yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were done euery moneth ones or euery weke / or yet euery daye, of them that haue abilyte and tyme therunto. I wolde thynke &amp; iudge it a deuoute and meritoryous ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruaunce. For thoſe perſones, that by any of theſe / or lyke meanes, done ſo prepare &amp; make them ſelfe redy to dethe: may be ſure neuer to dye ſodenly. For many perſones
<pb facs="tcp:5373:44"/> ben ſore affrayde of ſoden dethe / &amp; done ful hartely make prayer, that they neuer dye ſodenly. Let them vſe this maner / or ſome one of theſe formes and maner of exercyſes / &amp; they may be ſure of theyr prayer / that is, neuer to dye ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly. Study therfore good deuout ſoules, to be redy at euery houre / and pray vnto our lorde, that you may haue the wyll that ſaynt Paule had,<note place="margin">Phi. i.c</note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayde. I couet and deſyre / to be dyſſolued, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte this lyfe / and to be with Chryſt. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he brynge vs all that made vs. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The olde wretche youre aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red beademan of Syon Rycharde Whytford.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:44"/>
                  <p>¶ Imprynted by me Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Waylande / at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don within the Temple barre / at the ſygne of the blewe Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande. An. M.D.xxxvii.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:45"/>
                  <p>¶The werke for houſholders, nowe newly corrected and ſet forthe into a dyaloge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder and his houſholde / by a profeſſed brother of Syon Rycharde Whytford with an addicyon of polle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye for houſholdynge / ſet forth alſo by the ſame brother.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of Christ on the cross</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of Christ and a religious official</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:46"/>
                  <head>¶ Certayne ſmall werkes of a brothers of Syon Rycharde Whytforde. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The contentes of this boke.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>FIrſt a dyaloge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacyon, betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder and his houſholde.</item>
                     <item>¶ An other dyaloge betwene the curate and his ghoſtly chylde.</item>
                     <item>¶ Two maners of alphabetes / croſroes / called. A.b.c.</item>
                     <item>¶ A dayly exercyſe, and experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of deth / all duely corrected by the ſelfe auctour, and nowe prynted trewely.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The ſayd auctour requyred me inſtantly that I ſhulde nat prynte nor ioyne any other werkes vnto his. Specially of vncertayne auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. For (of late) he founde a
<pb facs="tcp:5373:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> werke ioyned in the ſame volume with his werkes / and bought and taken for his werke / and was nat his. But was put there in ſtede of a werke of his. That before was named amonge the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his boke. And yet his werke lefte out / as is contayned in this preface here vnto the reders.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Vnto the deuout reders, Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Whytforde a profeſſed brother of Syon / gretyng in our ſauyour Ieſu euerlaſtynge.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe and thynke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely good deuout reders / that whan you rede theſe pore ſymple werkes: ſome of you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue had mynde to rede them / wyll nowe meruayle to ſe and perceyue that theſe ben the ſame werkes that went forthe before, and nothynge chaunged in ſubſtaunce / but onely the tytle, and ſome fewe thynges added. Some other wyll paraduenture iudge or feare in me ambicyon that I wold ſeme to make many werkes / and yet dyd ſende forthe but the ſame, newely chaunged or diſguyſed. To ſatiſfye therfore your deuoute myndes with the trothe in trewe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence / there is none ſuch cauſe. But yet cauſes there ben dyuers appartaynynge bothe vnto you &amp; me. One cauſe is that I truſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely you haue them here in a more perfecte lettre than you had before. And alſo more truely prynted. For (of a ſuretye) the tother letter was moche vicyous and faultye / &amp; that in ſome places, that myght ſeme vnto my neglygencye. And alſo in the ſame volume or boke / is one of my workes left out / whiche werke is nombred amonge the contentes of the ſame volume and boke. And in ſtede of my werke, is an other heretyke or heretycall werke ſet in place / and the whole boke ſolde for my werke / whiche thynge is the moſt chefe cauſe of the ſayd muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon or chaunge. For that thynge dothe nat onely put me vnto infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye and ſclaunder: but alſo dothe put all the reders in ieopardye of
<pb facs="tcp:5373:48"/> conſcyence to be infecte and alſo in the daunger of the kynges lawes, for the manyfolde erronyous opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons that ben contayned in the ſame boke. Nowe iudge you (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout reders) whether theſe cauſes ben nat reaſonable for the ſayd mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon and chaunge. I praye you therfore of your charyte take all vnto the beſte. And by my poore aduyſe / rede nat thoſe bokes that go forth without named auctours. For (doubtles) many of them that ſeme very deuout and good wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: ben full of hereſyes. And your olde englyſſhe poete ſayeth. There is no poyſon ſo peryllous of ſharp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, as that is: that hathe of ſugre a ſwetnes. I wolde gladly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welth and nat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ieopardye of your ſoules our lord god, &amp; moſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu my iudge / who kepe you, and ſende you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> increaſe of grace. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5373:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Christ with the 12 apostles</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:49"/>
                     <head>¶A Dialoge or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacion bytwene the houſholder and his houſholde.</head>
                     <p>The ſpekers.</p>
                     <p>¶Fyrſt ſpeketh the houſholder &amp; than ſpeketh one of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde for all the reſidue.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>The houſholder.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood chylderne &amp; frendes: I had (of late) cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell to call you all to gether. And (for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) to ſhewe vnto you a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of lyuynge: fyrſt therfore lett vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydre that all we bene mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, as well the ryche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, the yonge as the olde, there is no difference, none excepte, all muſt nedes dye. And thoughe we lyue very lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, yet ſhall we dye ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb facs="tcp:5373:50"/> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lengeſt lyfe of this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, is very ſhorte. And yet haue we no certayne, ne yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture of knowlege, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / where / howe, or in what ſtate we ſhall departe this lyfe. And ſure we bene, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> as we bene founde at that tyme, ſo ſhall we be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and without reſpite or delay, forthwith ſhall we be preſented and brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyghe iudge, that can nat be deceyued, to make a counte of all our lyfe paſt, where no man of lawe may ſpeke for vs, ne any excuſe may ſerue vs. Our owne conſcyence ſhall there ſpeke and tell playne trouthe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out craft or diſſymulacion, and (in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, a twynclynge of an eye) ſhall clerly confeſſe all our hole lyfe, and euery wryncle and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te therof: whiche confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if our lyfe were good, ſhalbe vnto our great honour, comforte, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:50"/> &amp; ioye euerlaſtynge. And contrary, if it were euyl, it ſhalbe vnto our great ſhame &amp; rebuke, vnto our endles ſorowe &amp; payne and wo euerlaſtynge. We haue nede therfore to be well ware, howe we ſpende our tyme, howe we paſſe this lyfe, or rather howe this lyfe paſſeth vs. And moche ſhall it auayl and profyte vnto the helth of our ſoules: ofte ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for to remembre our laſte ende. The wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. vii.</note> ✿ In omnibus operibꝰ tuis, memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nouiſſima tua, &amp;c. In all thy werkes (ſayth he) reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre thyne endynge daye &amp; what thynges ſhall come vnto the at thy laſte ende, and thou ſhalte neuer do ſynne, ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue euerlaſtyngly therin.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶One of the houſhold.</speaker>
                        <p>Syr we all byſeche you, than, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you wyll ſhewe &amp; teche vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; meane our waye that you
<pb facs="tcp:5373:51"/> ſpeke of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶The houſhold.</speaker>
                        <p>The fyrſte poynte therfore of a good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is to entende and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good harte &amp; conſtaunte mynde, to auoyde ſynne, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to ſtudy howe to fle and beware of the occaſyons therof. And than to appoynte hym ſelfe vnto ſome cuſtumable courſe of good &amp; ꝓfytable exercyſe.<note place="margin">Pſalmo. xxxiii.</note> ✿ Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte a malo, &amp; fac bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. (ſaythe the prophete) Tourne awaye thy face, thy harte, wyll, &amp; mynde, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all euyll, and appoynte thy ſelfe to worke good werkes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶The ꝑſone of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſhold.</speaker>
                        <p>Syr, hyt is ſone ſayd, Fle euyll &amp; do good. But I pray you ſhew vs forther howe to do ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶The houſhold.</speaker>
                        <p>For a fourme therfore howe to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuaunce I ſhall ſhewe you my poore aduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. I ſpeke vnto you good ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and deuoute ſoules, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde
<pb facs="tcp:5373:51"/> fayne lyue well your ſelfe, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte all other vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Fyrſt than eueryche begynne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſelfe. And as ſone as you do awake in the mornynge, to aryſe for all daye. Fyrſt ſodeynly tourne your mynde and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto almyghty god, and than vſe (by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuall cuſtome) to make a croſſe with your tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be vpon your foreheed or front, in ſayng of theſe wordes. In no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine patris: and than an other croſſe vpon your mouthe, with theſe wordes, Et filii. And the thyrde croſſe vpon your breſte / ſaynge, Et ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſancti. Amen. And if your deuotion be therto, ye maye agayne make one hole croſſe, from your heed vnto your fete, &amp; from the lefte ſhulder to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght ſayng all together. In no mine patris &amp; filii et ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſancti. Amen. That is to meane, I do
<pb facs="tcp:5373:52"/> bleſſe and marke my ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cogniſaunce &amp; badge of Chriſte, in the name of the father, and in the name of the ſone, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of the holy ghoſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, the holy Trinite .iii. perſons and one God. Than ſaye or thynke after this forme. Good lorde god my maker &amp; redemer, here nowe in thy preſence, I do (for this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; for all the tyme of my hole lyfe) by queth and betake, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do frely gyue my ſelfe, ſoule and body, with all my harte and mynde vnto the, good lorde, and vnto thy handes to be thy bonde ſeruaunte for euer, accordynge vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promyſe made in my bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme at the font ſtone. And here nowe I do ratyfye and newly confyrme the ſame and do fully conſente in harte &amp; mynde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, neuer here after, by the helpe of thy grace, to contrary the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:52"/> but to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue in thy lawes, good lorde, vnto the ende of my lyfe. But where thou knoweſt, good lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I am a frayle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, infyrme, feble &amp; weyke, &amp; of my ſelfe prone &amp; redy, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought,<note place="margin">Geneſis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> viii.</note> worde and dede vnto euyll, from the begynnynge of my lyfe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: I beſeche the good lorde god and father of all puyſaunce &amp; power, of all myght &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght, that thou wilt defende me from all myne enemyes, and gyue me ſpirituall ſtrenght and power, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may / in the / vaynquyſſhe and ouercome, fle &amp; auoyde all ſuche fraylte, lyght maners or diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, as ſhuld be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to thy wyll and pleaſure, &amp; that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vnto this wyll of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whiche thy goodnes hath now frely gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me, I may deſtroye the wyll of the fleſſhe &amp; ſo contynue vnto the ende of my
<pb facs="tcp:5373:53"/> lyfe. And yet good lorde, where thou knoweſt alſo that I am but rude and vnlerned, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out wytte wyſdome and due knowlege of the and thy lawes, all ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and as an ydiote or foole in all good and ſpirituall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, I byſeche the good lorde god that art the eſſentiall ſone of god the father, and vnto whome is appropriate all wytte &amp; wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, all ſcience / connynge and knowlege, and all ryght percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge &amp; vnderſtandynge / that thou wylte graunte me the due knowlege of thy ſelfe by ryght &amp; true fayth, and the knowlege of all thy benefytes &amp; gyftes done to me and all mankynde / &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dewly to thanke the for them. And alſo due knowlege of myne owne ſelfe, of the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my lyfe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſpecially of my wretchednes
<pb facs="tcp:5373:53"/> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> due contricion for all my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And knowlege alſo of thy lawes, wyll &amp; pleaſure / ſo that by no maner of ygnoraunce or myſvnderſtandyng, I do (at any tyme) in werke or dede / or in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or thought: any thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the ſame. And thyrd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (good lorde) where y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knoweſte alſo that I am ofte tymes obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of mynde, froward &amp; euyll wylled / ſtubburne of ſtomake &amp; vnkynde of harte / dull / negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and ſlouthfull in all maner of goodnes, I beſeche the good lord god holy ghoſt / that arte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite and wyll of the father / &amp; of the ſone, and with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſelfe eſſenciall god, vnto whome is appropriate and ſpecially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted / all bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / all goodnes / all grace and good wyll, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldeſt voyche ſaffe to gyue me the grace of good wyll, ſo that I
<pb facs="tcp:5373:54"/> neuer do / ſaye / ne thynke that ſhulde be contrary to thy wyll. And hauynge vnto the euer a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de drede, I may loue the for thy ſelfe, &amp; all other in the (lorde) and for the / ſo that accordynge vnto the ſpirituall ſtrength and knowlege that thou haſt gyuen me, I may apply my wyll hooly vnto thy wyll / ſo that I haue no wyll propre vnto my ſelfe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my wyll be all thy wyll, &amp; bothe (as moche as maye be poſſyble) one wyll. And ſo I maye here in this life ordre my loue, and come vnto ſuche perfection of feruent charyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace) I may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge charyte in thy ioyfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And good lorde god father of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beſeche the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke &amp; receyue me thus vnto thy grace. and haue mercy and pyte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me and all thy people. And
<pb facs="tcp:5373:54"/> thou lorde God blyſſed ſone of god the father, and ſauyour and redemer of the worlde / haue py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mercy vpon me and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all Chriſten people. And louyng lorde god holy ghoſt and bleſſed ſpirite of god / haue mercy &amp; pyte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me and all the worlde. Holy and bleſſed Trinite, one ſelfe &amp; ſame eſſenciall god / haue pyte &amp; mercy vpon me and all myne / &amp; vpon all thy creatures. Amen. And than ones agayne bleſſe the with, In nomine patris: as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go forth vnto your buſynes where ye wyll. Let this be for your mornynge exerciſe. And though you that haue grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te thynges to do, wolde thynke this prayer and mornynge exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ouer longe, becauſe of your buſynes I acerteyne you, if it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes were by vſe goten redy and incorporate and prynted in the
<pb facs="tcp:5373:55"/> harte and mynde, it wolde ſone be ſayd or thought / and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſhulde (I byleue) haue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to ſpede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better in other thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and nothyng forthynke of the ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge of the tyme, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accounte it for greate gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in ſo moche that we purpoſe to ſet forth in the ende a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, for them that haue longer tyme to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, but nowe we ſhall go forth herin. After y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe exerciſe I truſte you wyll be well occupied vpon your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted courſe of occupacion. For that was our counſeyle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge, that ye ſhulde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynte your ſelfe, by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuall courſe, vnto ſome certayne occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacion that may be profytable, &amp; euer to auoyde ydlenes the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and nourſe of all ſynne and euyll. And euer beware of ſuche occupacions as ben called com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munly
<pb facs="tcp:5373:55"/> paſtymes, that is to ſaye, all maner of vnlawfull games / &amp; ſuche diſportes as done drawe people rather to vyce tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, whiche more properly maye be called loſe tymes than paſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. For ſyth / <note place="margin">Math. xii.c</note> by the affyrmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our fauyoure, we ſhall make accoumpte of euery ydle worde / it muſte nedes followe that we ſhall make a more ſtrayte reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of euery ydle or euyll wer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Let therfore your ſayd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted occupacion be alwaye good: vertuouſe and profytable. Syth tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye muſt nedes make a rekenynge of euery werke: wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and thought (for none of theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be hyd or kept preuy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your audytour) me thynketh it ſhulde be a greate ſuretye for you: to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke euery day ones your ſayd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te by your ſelfe. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune prouerbe is, that ofte rekenynge
<pb facs="tcp:5373:56"/> holdeth lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fellawſhype. I wold aduyſe you therfore to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me tyme ther vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at nyght after all your occupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, before your bed, there knele downe &amp; ther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre wheder ye we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; what ye dyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mediatly after your morowe exerciſe, &amp; in what company ye were, &amp; what was there your behauiour and dema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> werke, worde, or thought, and ſo go forth vnto euery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / tyme &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany as brekefaſte / dyner / ſoupper / or drynkynge / &amp; where you fynde or perceyue any thyng that was good / vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous / and profytable / aſcribe and apply that vnto our lorde god, &amp; gyue vnto him all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory, laude &amp; prayſe therof / for he alone is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyuer of all goodnes / &amp; ſo ouer paſſe that thynge lyghtly. And where ye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of any ſpeciall thynge done / ſayd / or thought
<pb facs="tcp:5373:56"/> amyſſe / flycke &amp; byde thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; bulte it (as they ſay) &amp; tourne it vp ſo downe / &amp; try the weyght &amp; daunger therof, with all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and circumſtaunce of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. So may ye knowe the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytie therof, that is to ſay, howe greate a ſynne or howe lyttell it is / howe be it, none offence cane be lyttell that doth offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de god, &amp; ſurely euery ſynne. is offence do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto god, although it ſeme to be done vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god doth begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neyghbour (For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth nat his neyghbour) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may ſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bodyly eye or ſyght (ſayth ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) howe may he loue god (whome he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat ſo ſe) ſo in lyke maner the offence of the neyghbour is forth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of god.<note place="margin">i. Ioh. ii.</note> Conſyder therfore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome the treſpas is done, &amp; ſo that conſyderacion with the
<pb facs="tcp:5373:57"/> other qualyties and quantyties of the ſynne, ſhall bryng you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a baſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof, and to be ſory therfore, or (at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt) to wyll or wyſſhe that ye had nat ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mekely crye god mercy / and aſke hym forgyuenes therof with very pourpoſe and mynde to be confeſſyd therof at due ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and to take and do penaunce therfore. And I dare aſſure you that this maner of accoumpte &amp; rekenynge (though your ſynne were neuer ſo greate) ſhall ſaue you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ieopardy of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which is no lytell grace &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God. Thanke hym than lowly therfore, and ſo bleſſe your ſelfe, as you dyd in the morning / and your bedde alſo / &amp; go there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte your ſelfe all hole body and ſoule vnto the protection / cuſtody and kepyng of our lorde, who gyue you good
<pb facs="tcp:5373:57"/> nyght and good reſte. Amen. It ſhall be ryght well alſo that ye cal vpon ſuche holy ſayntes as you haue ſpeciall deuocion vnto, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this fourme or ſome other ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Bleſſed lady Mary mother of god alway vgin, I beſeche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pray for me, &amp; for all Chriſtians. Holy angell of god, what ſo euer thou be that arte deputed and appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto my cuſtody, I (ſubmyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge me with moſt lowly obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) beſeche the to pray for me &amp; for all the worlde. Saynt Micha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell, ſaynt Gabriell, ſaynt Rapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, with all holy angels &amp; archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, I beſeche you pray for me &amp; for all people. Saynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſte and all holy patriarkes and prophetes: I beſeche you pray for me &amp; for all chriſtendome. Saynt Peter, ſaynte Paule, ſaynte Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euangeliſte, and all holy apoſtles &amp; eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes, I beſeche
<pb facs="tcp:5373:58"/> you pray for me &amp; for all the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and you alſo all diſciples of our lorde, and holy Innocentes. Saynte Stephan, and all holy martyres. Saynte Auguſtine / and all holy confeſſours / all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſones and heremites. Saynt Katheryne / ſaynt Marga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rete, ſaynte Barbara, and all holy virgines: I beſeche you praye for me / and for all perſones. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally all you holy ſayntes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of euery degre and ſtate where you be, I beſeche you all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall / and eueryche in ſpeciall / praye for me &amp; all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re may you brynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patrones of your churches or dioces, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as you haue (as I ſayd) ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler deuotion vnto. And here an ende as vnto your ſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶The perſone for the houſholde.</speaker>
                        <p>Syr / this werke is good for religious perſones / and for ſuche perſones
<pb facs="tcp:5373:58"/> as bene ſolytary: and done lye alo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe / but we done lye .ii. or .iii. ſomtyme together / and yet in one chambre dyuers beddes &amp; ſo many in company / if we ſhulde vſe theſe thynges in <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſence of our fellowes, ſome wold laugh vs to ſcorne &amp; moke vs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>¶The houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder.</speaker>
                        <p>O bone Ieſu. O good lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Ieſu, what here I nowe? I dar well ſay, there bene but fewe perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in Englande but they wolde byde ſome daunger or rebuke for pleaſure of theyr kynge or pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and many for theyr mayſter or maiſtres, or theyr ſoueraynes and ſome for theyr frendes and fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, &amp; ſpecially where great gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhulde growe therby vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe. And for the pleaſure of God our father, and of our ſwete ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Ieſu our brother, ſhulde we be abaſſhed to take dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; bere a poore mocke or ſcorne, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:59"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:5373:59"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:5373:60"/> ſhall wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our fleſſhe, ne yet tere our ſkyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of our pereles prynce kynge of kynges / &amp; lorde of all lordes? Fye for ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that any chriſtian ſhulde be ſo cowardous. Ventre vpon it, go forth withall. In .ix. dayes (as they ſaye) the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſhalbe paſt / fere nothinge. Euery begynnyng is harde and of greate diffyculte.<note place="margin">Omne principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a vincit.</note> But i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>portune labour doth vayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyſſhe &amp; ouercome all thynges. I tell you, this dayly exerciſe by cuſtome and vſe, ſhall ſeme very ſhorte and ſwete, profytable and pleaſaunt. Rede it or here it ouer ones or twyſe at the leeſt before you caſte it awaye. How be it we thynke it nat ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor ynough for vs to lyue well our ſelfe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all other chriſtians alſo lyue the better for vs and by our example, &amp; ſpecially thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; gouernaunce, that is to ſaye:
<pb facs="tcp:5373:60"/> our chylder and ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. And me ſemeth it ſhuld alſo be a good paſtyme and moche meritorious: for you that cane rede, to gather your felowes about you on the holy day, ſpecially the yonge ſorte and rede to them this pore leſſon. For therin be ſuche thynges as bothe you and they bene bounde to knowe, or can ſay: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter: the Aue maria: and the Crede / with ſuche other thynges as done folowe. I wold therfore you ſhuld begynne with them by tyme in youth as ſone as they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeke. For it is an olde ſaynge. The pot or veſſell ſhall euer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or ſmell of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is fyrſte ſeaſoned.<note place="margin">Quod no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua reſta capit: in ueterata ſapit.</note> And your englyſſhe prouerbe ſaythe / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong cocke croweth as he doth he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and lerne of the olde. you maye in youthe teche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ye wyll / and that ſhall they lengeſt kepe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5373:61"/> remembre. We ſhuld therfore abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue all thynges, take hede and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in what company our chylde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren bene nouryſſhed and brought vp. For educacion and doctrine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, bryngynge vp and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, done make the maners, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good and vertuous perſones (ſaythe the prophete) you ſhalbe good and vertuous.<note place="margin">Pſalmo. xvii.</note> And with the euyll perſones, you ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo euyll. Let our chylder therfore vſe and kepe good company. The pye, the iay, and other byrdes, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſpeake what they moſte here by eare. The plouer by ſyght wyll folowe the geſture and behauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the fowler. And the ape by exerciſe wyll worke and do as ſhe is taught / and ſo wyll the dogge (by violence) contrary to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſicion: lerne to daunce. The chylder therfore that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon don far excede other creatures
<pb facs="tcp:5373:61"/> wyll bere awaye what they here ſpoken, they ſhulde therefore be vſed vnto ſuche company where they ſhulde here none euyll / but where they maye here godly and Chriſtian wordes. They wyll alſo haue in theyr geſtures and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure ſuche maners as they ſe &amp; beholde in other perſones. And as they bene taught / ſo wyll they do / and in many thynges they maye be compelled vnto a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall cuſtome / whiche dothe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and chaunge naturall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion. Vnto ſome craftes or occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacions a certayne age is requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in chylder / but vertu and vyce maye be lerned in euery age. We muſt ſe therfore that in any wyſe you vſe no company but good and vertuous. And as ſoone as they can ſpeke: we muſt alſo teche our chylder to ſerue god and ſaye the Pater noſter. Aue. and Crede.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:62"/> as I ſayd before. And nat only our chylder, but alſo ſe and proue that all our ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, what age ſo euer they be of: ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay the ſame. And therfore don we vſe dayly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in euery mele / dyner or ſoupper / one perſone ſhulde with lowde voyce ſay thus.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>
                        <note n="1" place="margin">The fyrſt peticion.</note>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ater noſter qui es in celis: ſanctificet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tuum. ✿ Good lorde god, our holy father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arte in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let thy name he ſanctified: that is to meane / I beſeche the graunte vs grace to bleſſe, to honoure, to laude and prayſe thy holy name.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="2" place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde.</note>¶Adueniat regnum tuum. ✿Good lord god our father that art in heuen / let thy kyngdome come: that is, I beſeche the lorde, that all the people of the worlde may come vnto the grace of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:62"/> and ſo be the faythfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of thy realme and kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chriſtianite.</p>
                     <p>¶Fiat voluntas tua:<note n="3" place="margin">The thyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.</note> ſicut in celo et in terra. ✿ Good lorde god our father that arte in heuen, lett thy wyll be wrought in erth as it is wrought in heuen: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne I beſeche the lorde, that all thy chriſtian people here in erth maye perfourme thy wyll, and kepe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes after theyr eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and condicion, as thy holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and ſayntes done in heuen after theyr ſtate and degre.</p>
                     <p>¶Panem noſtrum cotidianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> da nobis hodie.<note n="4" place="margin">The four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the.</note> ✿ Good lorde god our holy father y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> arte in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, gyue and graunte vnto vs this day our dayly brede: that is to meane, I beſeche the good lord graunte vnto vs contynually the ſpirituall fode grace and effecte of thy holy ſacramentes. Or thus.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:63"/> Graunte vnto vs the contynuall grace and effecte of thy holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes / whiche is the dayly fode of our ſoules, &amp; ſpirituall ſuerty of our ſaluacion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="5" place="margin">The fyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the.</note>¶Et dimitte nobis debita no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra: ſicut et nos dimittimus debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus noſtris. ✿ Good lord god our holy father that arte in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, forgyue vs our dettes, as we done forgyue our detters, that is to meane, I beſeche the good lord, forgyue and pardon me and all Chriſtians all maner of offences and treſpaces done agaynſte the and thy lawes / lykewyſe as we done forgyue all maner of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes all maner of greues and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaces done agaynſte vs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="6" place="margin">The .vi.</note>¶Et ne nos inducas in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem. ✿ Good lord god our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father that arte in heuen / lede vs nat in to temptacion / that is to meane, I beſeche the good lord,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:63"/> ſuffre me not, ne any Chriſtian, to be lede or brought by any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation / vnto the full conſente of any ſynne.</p>
                     <p>¶Sed libera nos a malo.<note n="7" place="margin">The .vii.</note> ✿ But good lorde god our holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that arte in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, delyuer me &amp; all chriſtians from euyll: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to meane, I beſeche the good lorde / that not onely thou kepe me and all thy people from all ſynne and offence of thy goodnes / but alſo that thou wylte delyuer and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs quyte of all ſynnes paſte / and conſerue and kepe vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in the ſtate of grace. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So be it: that is to meane / good lorde we beſeche the that all theſe thynges maye come to paſſe in full effecte / accordynge to our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion and deſyre.</p>
                     <p>This prayer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pater noſter / is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt excellent prayer, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauyour made it hym ſelfe / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:64"/> and taught it to his diſciples.</p>
                     <p>¶The Aue Maria, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt pleſaunte prayer, and of moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure vnto our bleſſed lady, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one parte therof is the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angell Gabriell, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by immediatly after her conſente, ſhe conceyued the ſone of god in her wombe. And the other parte, was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto her by ſaynt Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, inſpired and moued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by the ſpirite of god the holy ghoſt. And therfore dowe ſet forth the Aue maria, after ſuche maner as we dyd the Pater noſter.</p>
                     <p>AVe Maria gratia plena dominꝰ tecum: benedicta tu in mulieribus et benedictus fructus ventris tui Ieſus. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Hayle Mari full of grace, god is with the. Bleſſed be thou amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g women, and bleſſed be the fruyte of thy wombe Ieſus Chriſte, god and man. Amen. So mote it be.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:64"/>
                     <p>¶That fyrſt worde Aue, whiche I do Englyſhe after the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne maner, hayle is a worde of ſalu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion, as we ſay in commune co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſes or metynges together. God ſpede you, god ſaue you, god bleſſe you. Good morowe / good eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, god ſpede, god be at your ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, god be at your werke, god ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de you, with ſuche other, after the maner of the countrey where it is ſpoken. And the laſt worde Amen, it is a worde of conſente or deſyre, that the mater ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before ſhuld vnderſtande what euery worde meaneth.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>¶Nowe doth folowe the Crede.</head>
                        <label>¶The fyrſte article.</label>
                        <item>CRedo in deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patrem omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentem:<note place="margin">Saynte Peter.</note> creatorem celi et terre. ✿ I byleue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almyghty, maker of heuen &amp; of erth. This terme: In deum / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:65"/> is diuerſly Englyſſhed, ſome done ſaye / in to god, ſome: inwardly in god / ſome: perfytly in god. But the mooſte commune vſe of the countrey of the vnlerned people / is to ſaye. I byleue vpon god and vpon his fayth / but all dothe mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in effecte / that the perſone hath perfyte faythe and byleue in god / and vnto god.</item>
                        <label>¶The ſeconde article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Andrew.</note>¶Et in Ieſum Chriſtum filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius vnicum dominum noſtrum. ✿ And I alſo byleue perfytely vpon our lorde Ieſu Chriſte his onely begote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſone: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begoten ſone of the ſayd father.</item>
                        <label>¶The thyrde article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Iohan.</note>¶Qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptus eſt de ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: natꝰ ex maria virgine. ✿ And alſo I byleue perfytly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our ſayd lorde Ieſu was conceyued of the holy ghoſt, borne of our lady ſaynt Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry: ſhe remaynyng &amp; abydyng euer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:65"/> euer a virgine.</item>
                        <label>¶The fourth article.</label>
                        <item>¶Paſſus ſub pontio Pilato / crucifixus mortuus et ſepultus.<note place="margin">Saynte Iames: the more</note> ✿ And alſo I perfytly byleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſayde lorde Ieſu dyd ſuffre his paſſion, &amp; was crucified, deed, and buried, vnder the power and iugement of a man called by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre name Poncius / and by his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde or ſurename Pylate.</item>
                        <label>¶The fyfth artycle.</label>
                        <item>¶Deſcendit ad inferna:<note place="margin">Saynte thomas of Iude.</note> tertia die reſurrexit a mortuis. ✿ And I byleue perfytely alſo / that our ſayd lorde Ieſu: after his ſayde paſſyon and dethe / deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and wente downe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lowe places of hell / and brought forthe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſe our fyrſte father Adam: and all that were there with hym / and that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thyrde day after his deth: he dyde aryſe from deth / and all the bondes therof vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5373:66"/> lyfe euerlaſtynge.</item>
                        <label>¶The ſyxth artycle.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Iames / the leſſe.</note>¶Aſcendit ad celos: ſedet ad dexteram dei patris oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>potentis. ✿ And alſo I byleue perfytly: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſayd lorde Ieſu dyd aſcende and ſtye vp vnto the hygheſt he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and ther doth ſyt vpon the ryght hande of god the father oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and almyghty.</item>
                        <label>¶The ſeuenth article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Philipe.</note>¶ Iude ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turus eſt iudicare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uos et mortuos. And I alſo ꝑfyte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly byleue, that he wyll come theſe agayne in to this worlde, to iuge all perſones quycke and deed.</item>
                        <label>¶The .viii. article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Bartel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewe.</note>¶Credo in ſpiritum ſanctum. ✿ I byleue perfytly alſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſt, the ſpirite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father and of the ſone, &amp; with them both the ſame ſelfe god.</item>
                        <label>¶The .ix. article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe.</note>¶Sanctam eccleſiam catholica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:66"/> ✿ I alſo byleue that the churche of Chriſte is and was / and euermore ſhalbe holy &amp; faythfull / therefore I do gyue fayth and crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the ſame, and vnto the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions therof.</item>
                        <label>¶The .x. article.</label>
                        <item>¶Sanctorum communionem:<note place="margin">Saynte Symon.</note> remiſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccato<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>rum</ex>
                           </expan>. ✿ I byleue alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſayntes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / I byleue that all the workes and good dedes of all good &amp; holy perſones / ben and ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune: ſo that euery faythfull Chriſtian hath &amp; ſhall haue part with other. And alſo I byleue the remiſſon of ſynnes: that is to ſay / that all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſynnes may and ſhalbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuen / if forgyuenes be duely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred and axed.</item>
                        <label>¶The .xi. article.</label>
                        <item>¶Carnis reſurrectionem.<note place="margin">Saynte Iude: cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led alſo ſaint Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deus.</note> ✿ I alſo byleue the reſurrection of our fleſſhe / that is to ſaye / I byleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                           <pb facs="tcp:5373:67"/> all maner of perſones ſhall aryſe at the daye of dome in ſoule &amp; body with the ſame fleſſhe, blode and bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that they were borne with and dyed with.</item>
                        <label>¶The .xii. article.</label>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Saynte Mathie.</note>¶Et vitam eternam. Amen. ✿ And I alſo byleue euerlaſtyng ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: that is to ſay, that (after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſurrection (all maner et per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones / as well good as euyll: dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pned or ſaued / ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue in lyfe euerlaſtynge, eyther in ioye or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; neuer departe therfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This worde Amen, is declared before in the ende of the Pater noſter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>¶This maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pater noſter, Aue, and Crede, I wold haue vſed &amp; rede vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the boke at euery mele / or at the leeſte ones a day with a lowde voyce (as I ſayde) that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſones preſente may here it. And yet forther I wolde aduyſe &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyle all other houſholders to ſe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:67"/> (as I do) knowe / and proue / that euery perſone in theyr houſe / &amp; all that ben vnder theyr gouernaunce and charge (can ſay the ſame) and therfore they muſte take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laboure to here them theym ſelfe, and wher nede is: to teche them. For many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben aged and can not ſay wyll be abaſſhed to lerne it openly, and yet if they here it dayly redde after the maner ſhewed before: they ſhall by vſe and cuſtome lerne it very well. And ſome other perſones the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re bene: that can ſaye ryght well / both vpon the boke and without, but yet amonge them ſome bene dulla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>des and ſlouthfull and ſome negligente and careles / and ſo done they not ſaye it: but in tyme forgete it / as in maner they hade neuer lerned it. I pray you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (good deuoute houſholders do as I do) take the payne to here them your ſelfe: at the leeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ones
<pb facs="tcp:5373:68"/> a weke &amp; let none eſcape you / olde nor yong. It ſhall (byleue me) be vnto you a great diſcharge of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and not without merite &amp; greate rewarde. And charge them ſtraytly vnder payne of punyſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / that they ſay it euery day thre tymes at the leeſt / that is to ſaye / in the mornynge / at none or myddaye / &amp; at nyght. Than muſt you teche them to knowe by ordre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preceptes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipall ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, &amp; of theyr .v. wyttes, as thus. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god ben .x. in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The fyrſt"/> The fyrſt that we ſhall haue no ſtraunge ne other godes. but one alone: and hym to loue. honoure &amp; drede aboue all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The .ii."/> The ſeconde we may not take the name of god in vayne, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may not vſe to ſwere. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The .iii."/> The thyrde, we muſt kepe our holy day with cloſe mynde vnto god, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende deuocion, and therfore we
<pb facs="tcp:5373:68"/> may do no bodely or worldly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for lucre therin. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".iiii."/> The fourth we muſte with reuerende and due lowly maner do honoure vnto our parentes, that is to ſay vnto our fathers and mothers, and we ſhall haue (by the promyſe of god (longe lyfe therfore. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".v."/> The .v. we ſhall not ſlee or kyll any perſone, neyther in dede: nor yet in wyll or mynde, nor yet may we hate any perſone in harte. For who ſo euer ſo doth:<note place="margin">i. Ioh. iii.</note> is an homicide and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſleer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".vi."/> The .vi. we maye do no lechery. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".vii."/> The .vii. we may do no thefte. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".viii."/> The .viii. we may bere no falſe wytnes, ne make any lye or leſynge. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".ix."/> The .ix. we may not coueyte or deſyre any wedded or maried perſone. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".x."/> And the .x. we may not coueyte ne deſyre any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mannes goodes. Theſe bene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by almyghty god / gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ben deuyded in two partes, as two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb facs="tcp:5373:69"/> or bokes.<note place="margin">Exod. xx.</note> The fyrſte appertey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth &amp; belongeth vnto almyghty god, hym ſelfe. And in that parte be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conteyned the thre fyrſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, and all thoſe thre commaundementes ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in this one commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the goſpell. Loue god aboue all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And in the ſeconde parte or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde table, bene the other ſeuen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned, whiche done apperteyne &amp; belonge vnto the neygbour. And yet all thoſe .vii. ben agayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this one commaundement of Chriſte. Loue thy neghboure as thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">A decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of the ſayde <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ceptes. The fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte.</note> ¶yet may you go ferther with them / ſome what to teache them what they meane. For whane you ſaye that we maye haue no mo goddes but one alone, that is to meane, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde loue nothynge ſo well as god. Whan ſoeuer that a perſone doth ſete his harte &amp; myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vpon any creature, more than
<pb facs="tcp:5373:69"/> vpon god / ſo that he wolde rather diſpleaſe god &amp; breake his lawes and ordynaunces, than for to leue &amp; forbere the affection or pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the creature / than hath he a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge god: a nother god, for tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thyng is his god / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he doth forſake god, and dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto his wyll &amp; ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And here (good and deuoute chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) be well ware, &amp; warne all yours of theſe ſuꝑſticious wytche craftes and charmes that bene moche vſed: and done deceyue many perſones, that (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue vnto the helthe of theyr bodyes, or of theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, or other goodes loſt or ſtole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) wyll go ſeke wyſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or wyſewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for ſo they don call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours that done vſe ſuche wytch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes and charmes) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſeke I ſay, and put them felfe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte vnto the falſe god the deuyll
<pb facs="tcp:5373:70"/> and his cerimonyes, to get helthe vnlawfully by the meanes of that wytchecrafte forboden by the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, vnder payne of curſynge. And yet the ſymple people, done ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; wene they do nothynge offend therin. For I haue herde them ſay full often my ſelfe. Syr we meane well / &amp; we done byleue well / &amp; we thynke it a good &amp; charitable dede to hele a ſeke ꝑſone / or a ſeke beeſt: &amp; trouth they ſay / but yet it is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good ne charitable to helpe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by vnlawfull meanes. And ſuerly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meane is vnlawfull. For good reaſon wyll admitte, that no ſore ſekenes may be heeled, but eyther by nature, or by medicine, or by my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racle. If a fynger be cutte, or ſmall ſurfet take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nature in a whyle wyll heele the perſone. But in all gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous diſeaſis, medicine is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune meane of helth: but ſure ben they that ſuche charmes or wytch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes
<pb facs="tcp:5373:70"/> be no medicins. For tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde they heele as well by one perſone as by a nother. And no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> byleueth they ben myracles ergo they muſte nedely by the deuels crafte, that do deceyue the ſymple perſones: dothe hurte ſome, &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> waye vnlawfully to brynge them in his dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. For you wyll grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te that he were a fole, that for the helthe of his horſe legge, wold loſe one of his owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, or one of his owne eyes / &amp; yet is he more fole in dede: tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for any creature wolde loſe his ſoule. But yet ſome haue ſayd to me. Syr / howe may this charme be euell or a mys, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thynges be good / as by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The charmer is a good man or a good woman, and taketh here a pece of whyte breade, and ſayde ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade nothynge: but onely the Pater noſter, &amp; maketh a croſſe vpon the breade / whiche thynges
<pb facs="tcp:5373:71"/> ben all good, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth he nothyng els but ley y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pece of breade vnto the toth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aketh or vnto any other ſore: tournynge the croſſe vnto the ſore or dyſeaſe, &amp; ſo is the perſone heeled. Howe maye this be euyll nowe ſay they? I ſay agayne it is euyll and dampnable, bycauſe the faythe &amp; byleue of the hole mater reſteth in that applycacion of the croſſe, whiche hathe no naturall oꝑacion, but is a cerimony vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full. For although all other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges here ben good, yet done they nothynge auayle without y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, &amp; ſo is all a charme and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lawfull and naught, whiche may euydently be knowen for nought &amp; vnlawfull, bycauſe the churche doth condempne &amp; forbede all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, whiche thyng ſurely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lerned churche of god, guyded euer by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt wold neuer haue done, if it were good and lawfull. And
<pb facs="tcp:5373:71"/> therfore in any wyſe, let none of your folks vſe any ſuche.<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde.</note> ¶Now for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde precepte, whiche is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no perſone ſhulde take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god in vayne, warne your folkes &amp; take good hede vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune ſwerers. For it were leſſe ieopardy for you to haue in your houſe a thefe or a ſteler, a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or vnclen lyuer, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an vſuall ſwerer. For a great othe accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, doth prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſodeyne ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god The ſcripture ſayth De domo iura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis non recedet pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ga. The cuſtomable ſwerer,<note place="margin">Eccleſi. xxiii. b.</note> ſhall euer be full of iniquite &amp; ſynne / &amp; the plage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vengeunace of god ſhall contynually ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ouer that houſe.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Let not thy mouth be vſed vnto ſwerynge (ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture) For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtomable ſwerer ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be clene purged of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I dare well ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwerynge is one of the great cauſes of all theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:72"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5373:72"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5373:73"/> ſodeyne plages amonge men and beaſtes, as peſtilence, pockes, ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges, and moreyns, with ſuche other. And I byleue verely none of you wold be glad to kepe in his hous a lepre, or any perſone infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any of the forſayd plages And yet is a ſwerer more peryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of them. For his othe may ſlee or infecte your chylde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cradle, or ſtryke your beaſtes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feeldes, deſtroy your corne &amp; gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and cauſe pryuely many myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheues. And yet many perſones done thynke &amp; byleue, that if they ſwere trouth, they do no ſynne, but they be ſurely deceyued, as by caſe. If a perſone wolde prynte &amp; coyne monye of good ſyluer or good gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, kepynge alſo the due weyghte and facion, that thynge wolde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge excuſe the perſone vnto the kynge or his lawes, thoughe alſo he proued the money were good &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5373:73"/> lawfull money. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges law is / that no perſone ſhall prynte or toyne any money but ſuche as be aſſygned by hym, and that alſo in the place appoynted thervnto. So in lyke maner, the lawe of god is: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no perſone ſhall ſwere any othe / excepte it be at the appoyntemente or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente of ſuche a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone that hath iuſt power to requy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and to take an othe, and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muſte be done in due place, that is to ſaye, before a lawfull iudge. And ſo may the perſone lawfully ſwere, ſo euer that the ſwerer do thynke and byleue in true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyned conſcience, that his othe is true. And els that is to ſaye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and ſuche other cauſes expreſſed in the lawe no perſone may ſwere, though it be neuer ſo true that he ſwereth. If than to ſwere true is ſynne, and dothe prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyghe diſpleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:5373:74"/> of god, by cauſe it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to ſwere falſe muſt nedes be more ſynne, &amp; more ꝓuoke his vengaunce. Example ſhall I ſhew here of both, that is to ſay, howe god is prouoked by vſuall ſwerynge, &amp; how by forſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge &amp; falſe othes. This ſtory y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foloweth I herde at Stondo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell vylage .xxv. myles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not farre from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyghe way vnto Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brydge / where for a tyme I dyd abyde in auoydynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greate pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both in London &amp; Cambryd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge dyde than quyckely &amp; ſharply reyne, where alſo this ſtory was open in the knowlege of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey there aboute, as don but ſmal tyme before. A gentylman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was called mayſter Baryngton whoſe wyfe was afterwarde maried in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brydge vnto a gentylman cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led maiſter Caryngton, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was but one lettre chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in her
<pb facs="tcp:5373:74"/> name, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay C. for B. And of her alſo I herde the ſame ſtory, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogh (as ſhe ſayd) ſhe was not pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent. This ſayd ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tylma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baryng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a great ſwerer, &amp; dyd cuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mably vſe greate othes: ſpecially by the blode of our lord, or (as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely they ſwere) by godes blode. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day or els a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtfull holy day he wente forth on hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng or hawkynge: &amp; nothynge ſpedyng after his mynde, he came vnto an alehous at a throughfare called Pulcriche .v. myles frome ware in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyghe way to Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brydge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche thorough fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd pariſſhe of Sto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where this gentylman was, &amp; called for drynk: &amp; anone he began to ſwere after his vnhappy cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſaynge. By godes blode this day is vnhappye. And in a whyle after in ſweryng ſo, he bledde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe, &amp; therwith more vexed he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane
<pb facs="tcp:5373:75"/> to rayle &amp; rayne god (as they ſay) in ſwerynge godes paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des woundes, godes fleſſhe, godes nayles, and euer his holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed blode, tyll at the laſte he fell fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to blede at the eares, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes, at his wreſtes, and all the ioyntes of his handes, and of all his body, at his nauyll and foundemente, &amp; of other places of his body, in mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelouſe great qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tite and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>emes of blode, &amp; ſhotynge cut his tonge in a meruelous horrible, vgſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e and ferefull maner, as blacke as pitche ſo that no perſone durſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me nere hym but ſtede a farre of, &amp; caſt holy water towarde hym / and ſo he conteynued euer ſwerynge / blaſphemynge and bledynge / iyll he expyred and was deed. And the more we after they layd hym in a carte / and caried hym to the ſayde churche of Stondon, and euer the body blede tyll he was buried in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5373:75"/> waye as they came in very greate haboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. This was a playn toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that god was moche diſplea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed with that ſwerynge, and dyde openly punyſſhe the ſame / in exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all vſuall ſwerers. It maye alſo be a good monicion and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge for ſuche ꝑſones that done myſevſe the holy day in hawkyng huntynge &amp; ſuche other fruytles occupacions or paſtymes. A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther example of the ſame vſuall ſweryng was ſhewed vnto me by a bacheler of diuinite called may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter George wercke / a fellowe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where I was alſo fellowe, of the quenes colege in Cambrydge, and after he was vycare of Harowe on the hyll, whiche thynge he ſayd vpon his conſcience. He ſawe him ſelfe in a marchauntes houſe in London, whiche was his ſpeciall frende, and ſente for hym to gyue counſeyle vnto the ſame perſone,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:76"/> a yonge man that was prentyſe: or els ſeruaunte vnto the ſame marchaunte / whiche yongman dyd vſe to ſwere for his commune othe / by the bones of god: or by godes bones. And it came to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that he was taken with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te meruelous ſekenes, ſo that no Phyſyke ne medicine myght hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ne eaſe hym, but that he lay ſtyl in bedde ſo longe, that the fleſſhe and the ſkynne of his armes and fyngers, and of his legges, thyes, ſhynnes / fete &amp; toes / dyd deuyde in ſondre / as though they had ben ſlytte with a knyfe, ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare bones myght openly be ſene and feled. And ſo in the ſame maner / (after he had with greate contrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and open co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of that ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge) receyued the ſacramentes of the churche / he departed this lyfe vnto our lorde. Here bene nowe two notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:5373:76"/> ſwerynge. The thyrde ſhall I ſhewe you of forſwerynge, or falſe ſweryng, whiche was ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me of an honeſt preeſt of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milier acqueyntaunce that was vycare of Halywell, where ſaynte Wenefredes well is, beſyde the ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bey of Baſyng werke in Flynt ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in the borders of Wales .xiiii. myles from Weſtcheſter, whiche thynge he ſayde on his conſcience he dyde ſe hym ſelfe and was ther preſent with greate multitude of other people thouſandes. A certey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne man was called to be ſworne in a greate mater bytwene two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whiche ſayd parties dyd put the mater hooly vnto the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his othe, and met bothe at a certeyne place where was a crucifixe: a holy rode that dyd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny myracles, whervpon he ſhulde ſwere, and ſo dyd in the ſyght and herynge of a great multitude of
<pb facs="tcp:5373:77"/> people gathred on bothe partyes. And his othe gyuen, he layd both his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vpon the fete of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rode / and ſware falſe &amp; contrary vnto his conſcience, and ſo was damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably forſworne, whiche thynge god wold haue knowen. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wolde haue taken his handes away to departe, both the handes cleued and ſtycked faſte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rode, as though they had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glued or faſtened w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nayles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And than he wolde with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence haue pulled them of: &amp; than with ſterynge and haſty mouyng to and fro, the ſteppe whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſtode: ſlypped and voyded frome hym. And than hanged he ſtyll by his handes, &amp; ſo remayned hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge ſtyll contynually the ſpace of thre dayes, &amp; maruelous moche people came thyther to ſe and loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, of the whiche many ben yet lyuyge. So at the laſte after
<pb facs="tcp:5373:77"/> thre dayes wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had with great contricion openly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute / &amp; receyued the ſacramentes of the churche, whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed &amp; thought verely he ſhulde there haue expired &amp; died he was ſodeynly loſed and delyuered / and lyued many yeres after a good &amp; holy lyfe / vnto the glory of God and great example of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bene ſwerers.<note place="margin">Lib. iiii. cap xviii</note> ⚜ Saynt Gregory in his dialoges doth ſhewe of a chylde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (as he had herd of other perſones) dyd ſwere great othes, &amp; had plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure therin, and ſodeynly whan he was ſwerynge in his fathers lap vpon his kne / the deuyll came &amp; openly rauyſſhed and by violence toke hym from his father / and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him away / that he was neuer ſene after. Here maye you percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the great peryll and ieopardy of ſweryng. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de therfore good deuout chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:78"/> take good hede therto / as well in your ſelfe as in your folkes. And yet ſhulde you haue no leſſe garde or awayte vnto lyeng, or makyng of lyes or leſynges. For the lye or leſynge is very mother vnto both the defautes ſhewed laſte before / that is to ſay, vnto periury or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweryng,<note place="margin">Menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium.</note> &amp; vnto falſe wytnes. For eueryche of theſe doughters / is worſe than the mother. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyer careth lytell to bere falſe wytnes / and euery lyer is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely a ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer / for els the lye ſhuld not be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured / dubbed and paynted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to ſeme true, &amp; ſpecially in a defaute whereof the lyer wolde fayne be excuſed for drede of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or rebuke, or wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhulde (by that lye) come to paſſe / &amp; be broughte aboute vnto effecte, for profyte, auauntage, fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery or pleaſure. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyer doth coueyte moſte ſubtelly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb facs="tcp:5373:78"/> &amp; fayne and gladly wold be byleued, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyer moſt lybe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally laſſhe out othes, &amp; ſparethe for no coſt (as they ſay) but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che a perſone doth ſwere moſt, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll a wyſe perſone byleue hym le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte. And by this doth appere, that the commune &amp; beſy ſwerers bene ſuſpecte to be lyers. For the lyer is combred ſo in conſcience, that he ſuppoſeth and thynketh he can not be byleued without he ſwere many othes, and great othes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware therfore of lyers. For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lyers bene communely theues or pyckers, &amp; vnclene lyuers. And (to ſay the trouth) the lyer is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; diſpoſed vnto all maner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, bycauſe that all lyers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> chylder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> was the fyrſte lyer, and eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue a lyer. And as the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſaythe, he is the father of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Nowe ponder and wey (go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute
<pb facs="tcp:5373:79"/> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) I pray you, if you were requyred whether you wold be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente to kepe in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany a thefe or pyker, a perſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld enforce and laboure to corrupte your wyues / or your doughters / or yet ſuche a perſone that were ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or chylde vnto your deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foo or enemy, I thinke you wyl ſay nay, you wold kepe no ſuche. Than ſay I beware of the lyer / for all commune lyers ben the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls chyldren, and done folowe theyr father the deuyl, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte and naturall diſpoſicion is to lye. I cane well graunte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>gyue and pardon them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, pyke, or do lechery: for ones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>yſe, and labour and loke for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ery and amendement, but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>yſe can I graunte that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>on the lyers, but euyn forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> you wolde cure the ſodeyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>lence: ſo correcte &amp; punyſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:79"/> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lye. Wherfor I haue ſet out here a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ty leſſon, whiche I pray you te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; euery chylde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cometh i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany you ſhall (I truſt) do moch good therby.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>¶If I lye, backebyte or ſtele</l>
                        <l>If I curſe, ſcorne, moke, or ſwere</l>
                        <l>If I chyde, fyght, ſtryue or threte</l>
                        <l>Than am I worthy to be bete</l>
                        <l>Good mother: or mayſtres myne</l>
                        <l>If in any of theſe nyne:</l>
                        <l>I treſpas to your knowynge</l>
                        <l>With a newe rodde and a fyne</l>
                        <l>Erly naked / before I dyne:</l>
                        <l>Amende me with a ſcourgynge.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>¶And than I pray you fulfyll &amp; perfourme theyr peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; requeſt, &amp; thynke it not cruelly / but merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe man ſayth,<note place="margin">Prouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> xiii d</note> who ſpareth the roode: hateth the chylde. And in a nother place.<note place="margin">Eccle vii. c</note> If thou haue chyldren (ſayth he) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:80"/> them betyme / &amp; hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnd whyle they bene yong, your dayly practyſe dothe ſhewe vnto you / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> if you powder your fleſſhe whyle it is new and ſwete / it wyll conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue good meate: but if it ſmell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for it be powdred, all the ſalte you haue ſhall neuer make it ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Powder your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore betyme and than you loue them, &amp; ſhall haue conforte of them. I dyd appoynte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> correction before vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother or mayſtres, for commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely they done take the laboure of that myniſtery and ſeruyce. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandynge there may be ſayd father or maiſter, &amp; the ſtaffe or fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the ryme be all one. But who ſo euer do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wheder it be in laſſhes, or in wordes, let it be done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the charite of our lorde / &amp; with a myld and ſofte ſpirite: that euer it be done for the reformacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the perſone / rather than for the
<pb facs="tcp:5373:80"/> reuengynge of the defaute, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhulde you neuer do any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of correction whyle you be vexed, chafed, troubled, wroth, or angry for any cauſe, but rather for that tyme deferre the correction, &amp; a nother tyme by good delybera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon take the perſones on parte / or if the treſpas be openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than do it openly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the lokers thervpon may be warned therby, and gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good leſſon before the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and tell them you do the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt your mynde compelled thervnto by conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and requyre them to put you no-more vnto ſuche labour &amp; payne. For if thou do (ſay you) you muſte ſuffre parte of the payne with me / and therfore you ſhall nowe haue experience and proue what payne it is to vs bothe. And than paye truely, and afterwarde forthwith forgyue them clerly and gentelly / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:81"/> ſo that they do nomore ſo. And in doynge thus correction / you may edyfye &amp; refourme the perſones / &amp; alſo meryte &amp; haue thanke of our lorde. Where if co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary you chyde brawle, curſe, and with vngoodly wordes rebuke, or ſtryke with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynes to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge your owne cauſe or appetyte / you ſhall rendre the perſones more ſtubbourne &amp; ſtyffe harted, and engendre in them an hatered toward you. And alſo not only loſe your meryte, but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue payne and the punyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, where the other correction done by ſobrenes, ſhall cauſe the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es to haue you in a reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de drede, and alſo to loue you, &amp; here afterward to blyſſe you, and pray for you. I pray you therfore, wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; deſerue both theyr blyſſynge and prayer / and alſo the blyſſyng and rewarde of our lord. But by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that communly all perſones
<pb facs="tcp:5373:81"/> done vſe to ſwere ſome othe / in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmynge or denyinge / that is in ſaynge ye, as grauntyng, or nay, as denyinge, whiche be ſeldome ſayd nakedly by them ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome addicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore I wold haue you in auoydyng of all vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne othes to teache your chyldren to make theyr addicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnder this fourme. ye father, nay father: ye mother / nay mother: ye brother / nay brother: ye ſyſter / nay ſyſter: ye ſyr / nay ſyr: ye dame / nay da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: or vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtates, maiſter / mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres / and ſo forth of all ſuche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune termes / as graundfather, graundmother: godfather, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother: vncle, aunte, coſyn / and ſuche lyke / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any other addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, or any of theſe founde othes, as by cocke &amp; pye, by my hode of grene, &amp; ſuche other. For Chriſte ſayth in the goſpell vnto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.<note place="margin">Math. v</note> Swere not you at all (ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:5373:82"/> he) in any wyſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to meane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully or in vayne. And the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſalmo. lxii.</note> ⚜ Laudabuntur oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s qui iura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in eo: quia obſtructu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt os loquentium iniqua. That is thoſe perſones that done lawfully ſwere in god, ſhalbe prayſed &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue rewarde therfore, &amp; the mouthe of euyll ſpekets ſhalbe ſtopped / and they put to ſhame and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. All this haue we ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the kepynge of the ſeconde precepte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.<note place="margin">The thyrde <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte.</note> ¶ Nowe for the thyrde commaundement. I praye you gyue good example in your owne ſelfe, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teche all yours howe they ſhulde kepe duely the holy day, that is to ſay (in aſmoche as conuenientely maye be) to be voyde of all maner of worldly &amp; bodyly laboures. I ſayde in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently may be. For people muſt haue meat &amp; drynke / the houſes muſte be appareyled / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:82"/> beaſtes muſte be cured and loked vnto. And very vnfayned neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or nede dothe excuſe in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. The holy daye is ordeyned of god and the churche, onely for the ſeruice of god. The due place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruyce is the churche. vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may conueniently come ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And to them that may not / euery honeſt place of good &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full occupacion is theyr churche. For God is there preſente where he is duely and deuoutly ſerued. Take the payn therfore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you may to go forth your ſelfe / and cal your folkes to followe. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ben at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, do nothyng els but that you came for, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke oft tymes vpon them that bene vnder youre charge, that all they be occupyed, lyke (at the leeſt) vnto deuoute chriſtians.<note place="margin">Mathei xxi.</note> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche (as our ſauyour ſaythe) is a place of prayer, not of claterynge and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:83"/> talkyng. And charge them alſo to kepe theyr ſyght in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr bokes or bedes. And whyle they ben yong / let them vſe euer to knele / ſtande or ſyte / &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to walke in the churche. And let them here the maſſe quyckly &amp; deuotly / moche parte knelynge. But at the goſpell / at the preface / and at the Pater noſter, teche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtande, and to make curteſy at this worde Ieſus, as the preſte dothe. Thus in the fore noone let the tyme be ſpente all in the ſeruys of god. And than in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after noone, muſte you appoynte them theyr paſtyme with great diligence and ſtrayte commaundement. Fyrſte that in no wyſe they vſe ſuch vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties as communely ben vſed, that is to ſay / berebaytynge and bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baytynge, foteball, teneſplaynge / bowlyng, nor theſe vnlawfull ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of cardynge, dycynge, cloſſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge
<pb facs="tcp:5373:83"/>
/ w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche other vnthryfty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtymes, or rather loſetimes: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (for a ſuerty) the holy day maye rather be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than if they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ploughe or carte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eſter day, ſo it were not done by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte or diſpiſynge of the commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of the lawe, ne for vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable couetyſe &amp; loue of worldly goodes. For ſynne dothe alwaye more defoule and breke the holy daye than doth any bodely werke or occupacion. Therfore let them beware of the tauerne &amp; alehouſe / for drede of dronkennes, or of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, &amp; of ſuſpecte places / or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> company, for fere of vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / or lechery / whiche thynges bene vnto youth moſte peryllous / &amp; of great daunger &amp; ieopardy of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupcion. Aſſigne you therfore and appoynte you them the maner of theyr diſportes, honeſte euer and lawfull for a reſonable recreacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:84"/> and (aſmoche as conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly may be (lett the ſexes be departed in all theyr diſportes, that is to ſaye: the kyndes, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by them ſelfe / and the women by them ſelfe. And alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointe the tyme or ſpace, that they be not (for any diſportes) from the ſeruyce of god. Appoynte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo the place, that you may call or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for them whan caſe requyreth. For if ther be a ſermone any tyme of the daye, let them be ther preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te all that bene not occupyed in nedefull and lawfull buſynes / all other layde a parte, let them euer kepe the preachynges, rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maſſe, if (by caſe) they maye not here both. To bye and ſell or bargayne vpon the holy daye / is vnlaufull: excepte it be for very nede. Charyte vnto the poore and nedy neyghboures, doth lawfully excuſe bodely or worldly labours vpon the holy day. Loke well you
<pb facs="tcp:5373:84"/> neyther do ne ſaye wylfully, and by deliberacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the holy daye any thynge that you knowe in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſhulde be contrary vnto the honoure of god, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> done you iuſtely kepe your holy daye. A very good ſure paſtyme vpon the holy daye, is to rede, or to here this boke or ſuche other good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe bokes, and gather therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as many perſones as you can. For I tell you there ſhulde be no tyme loſte, ne myſſpente vpon the holy daye. Lett this poore leſſon nowe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente you for theſe thre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes of the fyrſt table, whiche (as I ſayd) done appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; belonge vnto almyghty God hym ſelfe. A nother ſhorte leſſon ſhall we ſet forth for the commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes of the ſeconde table.<note place="margin">The .iiii. precepte.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And fyrſte the due reuerende ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure to be done of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the parentes, that is to ſaye / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:85"/> vnto theyr fathers and mothers, Teche your chyldren therfore to aſke bleſſynge euery nyghte kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, before they go to reſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this fourme. ⚜ Father I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you of bleſſynge for charite: or thus. Mother I beſeche you of charite gyue me your bleſſynge. Than let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father or mother hold vp both the handes, and ioynyng them bothe to gether, loke vp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently &amp; deuoutly vnto the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſay thus. Our lorde god bleſſe you chylde, &amp; therwith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a croſſe with the ryght hande o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the chylde / ſayng. In nomine patris et filii &amp; ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſancti. Amen. And if any chylde be ſtyffe harted / ſtubburne and frowarde, and wyl not thus aſke bleſſynge, if it be within age, let it ſurely be whyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a good rodde, and be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thervnto by force. And if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſones be of forther age, &amp; paſte
<pb facs="tcp:5373:85"/> ſuche correction, &amp; yet wyll be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynate, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſuche ſharpe &amp; greuous punyſſhement as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyently maye be deuyſed, as to fyt at dyner alone and by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe at a ſtole in the mydle of the hal / with onely browne breade &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and euery perſone by ordre / to rebuke them as they wold rebuke a thefe or a traytour.<note place="margin">Deute. xxi. d.</note> For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe ſuche chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were brought before the hole townſhype, that is to ſaye, the people of the cyte, or of that towne, &amp; there were they ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto deth. And certeynly I wold not aduyſe ne counſeyle any parentes, to kepe ſuche a chylde in theyr houſe, without great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and punyſſhement. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thynke it were moche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te for ther pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, oft tymes to ſhewe vnto theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what commodyties and profytes, and what perylles &amp; ieopardies done
<pb facs="tcp:5373:86"/> folowe the honoure and diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of the pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, accordyng vnto holy ſcripture. Some whereof I haue here ſet forth as is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the boke of the wyſe man called Eccleſiaſticꝰ,<note place="margin">Eccleſi. iii. a</note> in the thyrde chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. Thoſe perſones (ſaythe he) that bene the chyldren of Chriſte / ben alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of his church, &amp; all ſuche (as thoughe it were by naturall diſpoſicion) ben gyuen &amp; applyed of that godly diſpoſicion vnto obedience and loue. All you therfore that ben louyng chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be euer obedient vnto the iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcrecion of your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And ſo be you obedient in all your werkes, that you therby may be the chyldren of ſaluacion, that is to ſaye, that youre obedience be done with the very loue of your harte, vnfayned &amp; without diſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacion. For god hath ordeyned that the father ſhall haue due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure
<pb facs="tcp:5373:86"/> amonge his chyldren, &amp; the mother in lyke maner with lowly obedience. Thoſe perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done loue god, wyll pray vnto hym for the forgyuenes of theyr ſynnes, &amp; afterwarde wyll beware co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyne &amp; kepe them ſelfe from them. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayly prayer they ſhall graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be herde. And lyke as a perſone for the ſurete of his lyuynge here doth horde vp &amp; gather treaſure / ſo done they ordeyne for the ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of theyr ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that duely do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne honoure theyr parentes. This worde parentes doth ſygnifye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father and mother. Who ſo euer doth due<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y honoure his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ſhall haue ioy, pleaſure, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte amonge his owne chyldren. And who ſo euer is duely obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the father, dothe therby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſſhe &amp; moche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother And theſe perſones that done due honoure vnto theyr pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5373:87"/> haue longe lyfe, and in the daye of theyr prayer they ſhall gracyouſly be herde of our lorde, &amp; haue theyr petycion. Thoſe perſones that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a reuerende drede vnto our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de god, haue in lyke maner a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende drede vnto theyr parentes / and done duely honour them, and wyll do them ſuche ſeruyce, and in lyke maner as a bonde ſeruaunte ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld do vnto his lorde and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as well in werke as worde, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all pacience and gentylnes. Do therfore to your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes honoure and reuerence, that the bleſſynge of God maye therby lyght vpon you, and that bleſſynge ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne and endure vnto your laſt ende. The bleſſynge of the paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes doth fyrme and make ſtable y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſſeſſions and the kynred of the chyldren. And contrary, the curſſe of the parentes dothe eradicate &amp; rotewalt &amp; vtterly deſtroy bothe.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:87"/> Chylde, neuer take thou pleaſure ne pryde in the rebuke &amp; diſprayſe of thy parentes.. For that rebuke is not thy glory, boſte, nor prayſe, but rather thy confuſyon, ſhame &amp; rebuke. For the glory and prayſe of euery perſone, ſtandeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of the pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. And a great ſhame and rebuke is it vnto the chyldren, whan the parentes bene without honoure and reuerence. Good chyldren take good pacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce with the age of your parentes, and neuer diſpleaſe ne greue them in all your lyfe. And if they fayle i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wytte or vnderſtandynge, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſpeke or do any thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto your reaſon or wytte / take you pacience with them, &amp; let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater paſſe. And in no wyſe do you not diſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bycauſe of your owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth or better abilite. For the pyte and compaſſion that you haue vnto your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:88"/> be forgoten before God. For you ſhall haue good and profyte of theyr offence &amp; ſynne. And in the iuſtyce &amp; ryght you do vnto them ſhall you be edifyed, and encreace in vertue. And i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of your trybulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that good dede ſhalbe remembrede. For as the yce in the froſt doth melte by the clere ſonne beames, ſo ſhall your ſynnes (by your duety done vnto your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be waſted and clene loſed &amp; for gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That perſone is of euyll na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and fame that doth forſake the parentes in theyr nede. And tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe chyldren bene accurſed of god, that done anger, vexe, &amp; trouble theyr parentes. Chylde of what ſtate or degre ſo euer thou be, do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thy duty with myldenes, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, and lowlynes, &amp; than ſhalt thou be well byloued, and prayſed aboue other perſones. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hyghe eſtate thou come vnto, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5373:88"/> more meke and lowly be thou in all thynges, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of god haue great meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and encreaſe in grace. For God doth loke vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that done ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre &amp; gyue due thankes, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure &amp; goodnes done vnto them before.<note place="margin">Ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata.</note> All this nowe is the very texte and lettre of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the place before reherſed. Where you may ſe &amp; perceyue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny great commodytes and graces that done come vnto them that duely don honoure theyr pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. And many great ieopardyes and peryles, and alſo the curſe of god / that doth lyght vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll not do theyr duety of honour and reuerence vnto theyr parentes. Let therfore your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe and accuſtome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe, dayly to aſke theyr fathers and mothers bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges. For this dare I ſaye, that although in caſe the father or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:5373:89"/> were an abhomynable ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">Er Gre. lib. d alo. iii. ca. vii.</note> or excommunycate, accurſed / or an heretyke, &amp; though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde were ſo alſo. yet myght that croſſe of the bleſſynge of that father or mother ſaue that chylde frome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne myſchefe, that els myght ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue come vnto that chylde. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe may alſo do flee or chace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way euyll ſpirites, that els ſhulde haue had power vpon that chyld. The bleſſynge of euery good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is good &amp; not without greate vertue, accordynge vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power and degre of the perſones &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore teche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo to aſke bleſſyng of euery biſſhope, abbote &amp; euery preſte, and of theyr godfathers &amp; godmothers, with other deuoute perſones. And let this ſuffyſe for this fourthe commaundemente. ¶yet go ferther vnto the fyfthe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente, whiche is to kyl or ſle no perſone. Teche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:89"/> that it is not ynoughe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they put no perſone to deth by ſtroke of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or wepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo that they hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te no perſone in name or fame by detraction, backebytyng or ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge, or by euyll example of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, nor yet that they curſe or banne or wyſſhe euyll vnto any perſone, or yet hate any perſone in herte.<note place="margin">i. Ioh. iii.</note> For (as ſcripture ſayth) who ſo euer dothe bere in the harte or mynde any hatered, malyce, euyll wyll, or ſtomacke agaynſte any chriſtian, is an homicide, that is a manſleer or a manqueller. Many perſones wyll ſay they ben in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, and haue no hatered vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſone, and yet wyll they not ſpeke one to a nother and that is a ſygne and token that preuy hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is in the harte, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not loue theyr neyghboure as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, in the true and vnfayned cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte of our lorde. And ſure it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5373:90"/> who ſo euer dothe not hooly and fully loue his neyghbore,<note place="margin">i. Iohan. iiii. d.</note> whome he may ſe &amp; behold with his body<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſyght, he cane neuer loue god / whome he cane not ſe, nor ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde. This is than the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God: that who ſo euer doth loue god muſte alſo loue his neyghboure.<note place="margin">The .vi. precepte.</note> The ſyxthe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is that no lechery be done / whiche is not mente onely for the vnlawful dede, but alſo for all ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of prouocacion therunto / as wanton and lyght behauyours, in kyſſynge, clyppynge, and vnclene touchynge,<note place="margin">Math. v d.</note> a lyght loke or caſte of the ſyghte, with a deſyre and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente of harte vnto the dede, dothe breke this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Moche more than doth rybauldy breke it, and ſuche maner as before is ſayd. The olde prouerbe ſayth. Who ſo wyll none euyll do: ſhulde do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge that longeth therto. The
<pb facs="tcp:5373:90"/> ghoſtly enemy dothe deceyue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſones by the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loure of matrymony, in pryuate-ſecrete contractes.<note place="margin">Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes.</note> For many men whan they cane not obteyne theyr vnclene deſyre of the woman, wyll promyſe mariage, &amp; thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a contracte promyſe, and gyue faythe and trouth eche vnto other ſaynge. Here I take the. N. vnto my wyfe, and therto plyght y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my trouth. And ſhe agayne vnto him in lyke maner. And after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> done / they ſuppoſe they may lawfully vſe theyr vnclene behauyoure / &amp; ſomtyme the acte &amp; dede doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god &amp; theyr owne ſoules. It is a greate ieopardy therfore to make any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che contractes, ſpecially amonge them ſelfe ſecretely alone without recordes, whiche muſt be two at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt. For many tymes after the vnlawfull pleaſure is paſte, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde
<pb facs="tcp:5373:91"/> dothe fall bytwene the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, eyther bycauſe that (as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mune prouerbe ſayth) hote loue is ſone colde,<note place="margin">ii. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiii. c</note> or els by the meanes of theyr frendes, or by ſome couety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to haue a better mariage they or one of them done denye the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte, &amp; ſo vnlawfully done mary otherwyſe and lyue in aduoutry all theyr lyfe tyme. And bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche cane not openly knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng that was ſpoken and done in priuyte, they bene thought and ſuppoſed ſo to lyue as lawfully in mariage, wher in dede before god they done lyue as noughty packes in dampnable aduoutry and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull lechery, and all theyr chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren baſtardes before God, all though they ſeme otherwyſe vnto the worlde. Warne therfore your folkes ther be no ſuch blynde bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynes in youre houſe or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. ¶The .vii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:5373:91"/> is, do not thefte. Herin cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte your yong perſones betyme.<note place="margin">The .vii. precepte.</note> For the chylde that begynneth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yke at a pynne or a poynte, wyll after pyke a peny or a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And ſo go forth from an apple vnto an oxe, and from a pere to a purſe, or an horſe, &amp; ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſmal thynges vnto the greate. Whan you take any chyld therfore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, be it neuer ſo lytle a thynge: pay truely at the fyrſte tyme, and the ſeconde tyme: and prycke the pynnes or the poyntes vpon the cappe or ſhulder in open ſyght, &amp; let all the houſe wonder vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and crye all: here is the thefe, this is the thefe, ſe ſe the thefe. And if they me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de not therby, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo brought through the open ſtretes with ſhame ynoughe, &amp; cruell pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhement. For better is it that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde wepte in youth, and ſuffre ſhame and rebuke, than herafter
<pb facs="tcp:5373:92"/> the father, mother &amp; frendes ſhuld wepe for ſorowe and ſhame at his hangyng and ſhamfull deth. And let euery perſone beware of thefte For all other ſynnes with contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / confeſſyon and penaunce / may be forgyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clerely, but thefte and all goodes vnlawfully gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / can neuer be forgyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that reſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be made that is to ſaye, vnto the tyme thoſe goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / or the valure of them be reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, if the perſones (in any wyſe) maye be able therunto. Lett euery perſone po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der well and wey, what vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage it is to ſtele or pyke, ſyth (beſyde the payne certaynely to be ſuffred in hell) the ſame goodes (in valure) muſt be reſtored agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Small goodes truly gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne growe and encreaſe vnto the greate conforte of the perſones- And contrary, euyll gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goodes lyghtly come (as they ſaye) and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:92"/> lyghtly go, all waſt vnto nought, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſconfort of the parties / &amp; great combraunce of conſcience. Se than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all goodes be well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten amonge you. ¶Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .viii.<note place="margin">The. viii precepte.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you haue before ſome reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce in the leſſons of ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng &amp; lyeng. ¶ The .ix.<note place="margin">The .ix. precepte.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is that no perſone ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre in mynde nor wyſhe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded make of any other perſone were lawfully theyr weded make.<note place="margin">The .x. precepte.</note> ¶And the .x. commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is in lyke maner of the goodes. For ſo ſhulde the parties haue incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modite, loſſe, diſpleaſure or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte. The dedes of theſe two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes were forboden of god in the .vi. and .vii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, here nowe bene the wylles and deſyres forbode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That thyng than that no man maye lawfully wyll: may no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do lawfully. Let them therfore beware that do not
<pb facs="tcp:5373:93"/> onely wyll and deſyre in mynde / but alſo done ſecretely, pryuely / and craftely laboure to take theyr neyghboures fermes, or his houſe (as they ſaye) ouer his heed, or to entyce and get away theyr ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, or any other goodes profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the parties. For though ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynges maye ſeme vnto the worlde lawfull, ſurely they be not without the great offence of god / as contrary vnto his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. And thus an ende of the .x. commaundementes.<note place="margin">Of the ſeuen pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipall ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</note> ¶yet muſte you haue a leſſon to teche your folkes to beware of the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryncipall ſynnes, whiche ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely called the .vii. deedly ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but in dede they do call them wronge, for they bene not alway deedly ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. Therfore they ſhuld be called capitall or principall ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: and not deedly ſynnes. Theſe bene theyr names by ordre, after
<pb facs="tcp:5373:93"/> our diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pryde / Enuy / Wrath Couetyſe / Glotony / Slouth / and Lechery. Thus don we ordre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / accordynge vnto our thre ghoſtly enemyes / the deuyll / the worlde, &amp; the fleſſhe. For Pryde, Enuy, and Wrath, done apperteyne and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the deuyll, as chefe mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And couetyſe dothe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyne vnto the worlde, as che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe mouer therof. And glottony / ſlouth / and lechery, done belonge vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe / as theyr chefe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, whiche thre we done put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this ordre, bycauſe that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony is a great occaſyon of ſlouth. For (as the prouerbe ſayth) Whan the bely is full, the bones wolde haue reſte. The full fedde glotton is apte vnto no good werke or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, but rather all diſpoſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſluggyſſhenes and ſlouth. And thoſe two betwene them done ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and ꝓuoke moſt vnto lechery.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:94"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The .v. wyttes.</note>¶Teche them alſo to knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of the fyue wyttes, and to put the fyrſte fynger of the ryght hande vnto the inſtrumentes of the ſame wyttes, that is to ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eare, the eye, the noſe, the mouth, and than to ioyne &amp; clappe both the handes togeder, ſaynge thus. Herynge, ſeynge, ſmellynge, taſtynge, and touchynge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The .vii. werkes of mercy.</note>¶It ſhalbe alſo well done to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .vii. workes of mercy. which you ſhuld (after your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) ſet forth in werke as you teche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in voyce. That is to fede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry. To gyue drynke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſty. To cloth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naked. Herborow or lodge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayfarynge folkes / or them that haue nede of lodgynge. Viſite the ſycke. Redeme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And bury the deed. Here is now an ende hereof.<note place="margin">A fourme of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> ¶Not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng I thynke it neceſſary to ſhew here yet howe as I lerned of my
<pb facs="tcp:5373:94"/> goſtly father y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taught me all this leſſon you ſhuld teche your folkes to be ordered vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confeſſyon of theſe thynges. For I haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many come vnto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could not tell howe to do, or what to ſay there. I ſhall therfore ſet forth he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a ſhort forme and maner therof. For ther ben many formes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions in print ſet out at lengh. Fyrſt good deuout chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you gyue no crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the falſe heretykes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done depraue &amp; ſet nought by confeſſyon, nor by this holy ſacrament of penaunce. For I acertayne you thoſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes what ſo euer they be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (after theyr baptyme and chriſtendome) haue done any deedly ſynne, cane neuer be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of ſaluacion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fayth &amp; wyll of confeſſion.<note place="margin">Gene. iii.</note> For almyghty god in euery lawe dyde requyre confeſſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke euery treſpaſſer thervnto, as
<pb facs="tcp:5373:95"/> of our fyrſt parentes Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Eue in paradyſe, whiche confeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they had mekely made, they &amp; we ſhuld haue ſuffred the leſſe payne.<note place="margin">Leuit. iiii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. v.</note> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe ſpeciall oblacions and ſacrifyce was appoynted ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly by the preſtes to be done for ſuche ſynnes amonge the people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were preuy vnknowen vnto all other perſones, excepte onely the ſelfe treſpaſſers, wherby it muſt nedes be trouth, that they were confeſſed therof vnto the preſtes. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any perſone alſo was ſuſpecte of lepry, the iugement and determynacion therof remayned (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe) vnto the preſte. Whiche thyng was a playne figure of the ſacramente of penaunce and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon.<note place="margin">Math. v</note> And our ſauyoure ſayde, he came not to breke the lawe: but rather to accomplyſhe and fulfyll the lawe. And ſo he dyd confyrme and ratifye that lawe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſent
<pb facs="tcp:5373:95"/> the lepres that he cured and heled vnto the preſtes.<note place="margin">Math. viii. Luc. xvii.</note> And i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery cure he dyd vpon the ſyke perſones, he expreſſed myſtycally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon, in that he cauſed them to ſhew theyr diſeaſe before they were cured. And ſaynt Peter his apoſtle after his aſcenſion, dyd requyre confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of a man called Ananye,<note place="margin">Acto. v.</note> &amp; of his wyfe called Saphirye (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth in holy ſcripture) of a deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne, whiche he (by the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of god) knewe they had done / and bycauſe they wolde not make confeſſion therof, they were bothe ſtryke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deth with the vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god. Our mother holy churche therfore hath (by the inſpiracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt) ordeyned that euery perſone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte or do any deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> werke, worde, or by full deliberate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente in thougt, muſt nedely (if they wyll be ſaued) be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed therof vnto a preſte. Sythe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:96"/> than all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vſed the ſame ſo many hondred yeres, take you that vſe &amp; cuſtome for ſufficient auctoryte to folow the ſame and to put all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of contrary opinion clene out of mynde, and in no wyſe to here ſpeke or talke therof. Nowe vnto our mater. Fyrſte teche your f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to come reuerently vnto the ghoſtly father with meke &amp; ſobre countenaunce &amp; behauyour. (For it is no laughynge gaine.) Than knele down at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place appoynted &amp; there make a croſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heed or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, with In nomine pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris (as before is ſhewed) and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth with ſay thus. Benedicite. And whan the preeſt hath anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, than ſay (if the perſone be ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) Confiteor deo, beate Marie, omnibꝰ ſanctis, et vobis, peccaui nimis, cogitatione, locutione, et opere mea culpa. that is to ſaye for
<pb facs="tcp:5373:96"/> the vnlerned, I confeſſe &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege my ſelfe gylty vnto our lorde god, the bleſſed lady ſaynt Marie, vnto all the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and vnto you my ghoſtly father y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue offended my lord god ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes in my lyfe, and ſpecially ſyth the laſte tyme of my confeſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in thought, worde, and dede, in many and dyuers wayes, mo tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I can ſhewe, ſpecially in the ſeuen pryncipall ſynnes. Pryde, enuy &amp; wrath, couetyſe, glotony, ſlouth, and lechery. And by them I haue broken his commaundementes-</p>
                     <p>¶Pryde.</p>
                     <p>¶For by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of pryde I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben preſumptuous &amp; diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto god, &amp; haue not loued hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue all thynges, but many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſet more by myne owne frayle appetyte and ſenſuall deſyre. For where I ſhuld haue deſyred euer
<pb facs="tcp:5373:97"/> the laude and prayſe of our lorde / and with all mekenes of hart ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed my ſelfe / I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted my ſelfe, or deſyred and bene glade of myne owne prayſe &amp; bene loth to be diſprayſed. And whan I haue ben chalenged, reproued, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, or corrected, or yet chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ben monyſſhed and warned of, and for my defautes, I haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>belled there agaynſt, and not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely receyued it but rather ben re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to defende or to excuſe my ſelfe, and ſomtyme with a lye, or a falſe othe. And for lacke of reuerende drede and loue of our lorde, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue by preſumpcion of pryde taken his holy name in vayne, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfuly ſworne by god, by our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſayntes by my faythe or trouthe, with ſuche other. And for very pryde and preſumption, and for lacke alſo of loue &amp; drede: I haue myſvſed the holydaye, in
<pb facs="tcp:5373:97"/> thynges of pleaſure, or profyte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to my ſelfe, and not in his ſeruyce vnto his honoure. I haue alſo (of hyghe &amp; proude harte or mynde) bene diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and not done due honoure and reuerence vnto my fathers and mothers ſpirituall &amp; carnall, ghoſtly &amp; bodyly, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to myne elders and betters, but haue ben many tymes full obſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and frowarde vnto them. I crye God mercy. Thus (by this foule ſynne of pryde) I haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foure of the principall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes of our lorde, and many other wayes haue I alſo offended therin. I beſeche his grace of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and forgyuenes.</p>
                     <p>¶Enuye.</p>
                     <p>¶I haue alſo offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded my lord god in the ſynne of enuye: for I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue not loued my neyghbour as my ſelfe, nor ben ſo charitable, ſo kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ſo louynge and fauorable vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5373:98"/> all perſones: as I wold they ſhuld haue ben to me, but rather I haue (by ſuſpicion) thought, iuged, ſayd or herde of other perſones, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe than I wolde they ſhulde of me, nor ben ſo glade of theyr wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, ne ſo ſory for theyr hurte as I wold haue ben of myne owne. I crye god mercy.</p>
                     <p>¶Wrathe.</p>
                     <p>¶In wrath alſo I haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for lacke of due pacience, and for lyght, ſlyght. or ſmall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, haue leyghtly &amp; ſoone ben ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; moued, wroth &amp; angry, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thynge hath ben done or ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto my mynd. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with haue ben redy to reuenge the ſame with froward and ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable countenaunce and behauyoure / with hyghe, haſty, and vngoodly wordes, brawlyng, chydyng, ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, reuylynge, rebukynge, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, vpbraydyng, thretyng, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:98"/> bannyng, ſweryng. And if it came thervnto, in ſtryuyng, fygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, or (at the leſt in wyll: as god forbede) i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyllyng or ſleyng. Thus by theſe two great ſynnes of enuy &amp; wrath I haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .v. &amp; the viii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of our lorde, in them both. I beſeche his grace of mercy and forgyuenes.</p>
                     <p>¶Couetyſe.</p>
                     <p>In couetyſe alſo I haue ſynned bycauſe I haue not bene contente with the goodes, ſtate, and degre of lyuynge that god hath ſente me where it is moche better than I haue deſerued, or am worthy, but I haue coueyted and deſyred / wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; wylled, ſtudyed &amp; laboured to haue more (if any be vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goten or ſo with holden, make playne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon therof as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requyreth.) Thus by this ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of couetyſe haue I broken the vii. commaundement of our lorde
<pb facs="tcp:5373:99"/> and the tenth and otherwyſe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly offended in couetyſe. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche his grace of mercy and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuenes.</p>
                     <p>¶Glotony.</p>
                     <p>¶I haue alſo ſynned in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, in takynge meate &amp; drynke vndiſcretely / and aboue that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dyde requyre, &amp; haue pycked out &amp; choſen (ſomtyme by ſenſuall appetyte) the delycate ſwete and pleſaunt meates and drynkes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for pleaſure tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for nede / and taken therof ſuche ſuperfluyte (at ſome tymes) that I haue ben ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſycke or diſeaſed, or at the leſte ben the more dull bothe in body &amp; ſoule, vnto all maner of vertue &amp; good exerciſes (loke here whether you haue broken any faſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the law, or ben dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, or taken any notable ſurfet) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meat commonly I haue bene more redy to paſſe the tyme in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly
<pb facs="tcp:5373:99"/> diſportes and ydlenes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in labours. I crye god mercy.</p>
                     <p>¶Slouth.</p>
                     <p>¶I haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo moche ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neglygent to ſerue God, both vpon the holy day and other dayes alſo, and I haue ben yrke wery, &amp; thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of prayer longe, come late therunto, &amp; make haſte therin, and ouer paſſed the ſeruyce of god, without due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, more by courſe and cuſtome than by any good remembraunce or deuocion, and alſo I haue not ben dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to apply my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuche bodyly labours as I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue had in charge &amp; ſometyme ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not done the labours at all, or els full ſleyghtly done them, and ſpent the tyme after myne owne appetyte full vnfruytfully, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme in wantonnes, &amp; ſometyme in very ydlenes. I crye god mercy.</p>
                     <p>¶Lechery.</p>
                     <p>¶By the meanes of theſe two
<pb facs="tcp:5373:100"/> foule ſynnes of glotony &amp; ſlouth / I haue bene the more redy vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde ſynne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe, that is to ſay lechery, for I haue not bene ſo chaſte in ſoule &amp; body as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate / degre &amp; maner of my lyuyng doth requyre, not ſo diligent &amp; ready to put awaye vnclene thoughtes or mocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body as I ſhulde be / but rather folowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes wyllfully, &amp; ſuffred them to hange vpon me, &amp; taken in them delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and pleaſure for the tyme. And whan I haue ben in <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſence of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, I haue not alway ordered my ſelfe in chaſte maner in my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes or ſyghtes, countenaunce and behauyour, wordes &amp; dedes, but many tymes haue ben full lyght to take or to gyue occaſyon. I crye god mercy. Here muſt you reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre ſute or prouocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, done or ſuffred on your behal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, as i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes, wrytyngs, ſygnes tokens, meſſages, kyſſynge, clyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:100"/> touchyng, or other more fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy and vnlawfull behauyoure / done in dede or in full conſente. And ſo ſhewe euery thynge with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due circumſtances, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and perſones, not namynge the perſones, but ſhewynge the ſtates or degrees of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as whether they he maried or vnmaried. &amp;c. Thus by this foule ſynne of lechery: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .vi. &amp; alſo .ix. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, and by many other meanes, as well in this ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as in all the other of theſe .vii. pryncipall ſynnes, haue I gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offended my lorde god, bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of mercy vnto my power, and myſvſed my fyue wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in herynge, ſeynge, ſmellyng, taſtynge, and touchynge. For the whiche &amp; for all other, as our lord knoweth me gylty, and I wolde confeſſe &amp; knowlege if they came
<pb facs="tcp:5373:101"/> to mynde, I beſeche his gracious goodnes of mercy &amp; forgyuenes. And you my ghoſtly father of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and abſolucion. Et precor ſanctam Mariam, omnes ſanctos dei, &amp; vos orare pro me. Whiche is to meane vnto the vnlerned. And I beſeche the bleſſed lady ſaynte Mary, all the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; you alſo my ghoſtly father to pray for me. And whan you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue taken your penaunce, and haue ben aſſoyled, than ſay you vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſte. Syr / and it pleaſe you, this is my penaunce, and than reherſe the ſame ones or twyſe your ſelfe / that you may the more ſurely bere it in mynde. For I aſſure you, it is ieopardeous (after lerned men) to forget the penaunce. And thus an ende therof. ¶yet dyd I promyſe in the begynnynge / to ſet forthe here a forther exerciſe, whiche I thynke ſhulde be good and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:5373:101"/> for all perſones. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune prouerbe is, that a great be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefyte or gyfte is worſe than loſte vpon ſuche vnkynde perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre it, ne gyue due thankes therfore. It ſhuld become therfore euery faythfull chriſtian to haue euer in mynde the greate and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t benefyte of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And therfore haue I deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here a ſhorte table, that dothe (in ſome) conteyne the hole lyfe of our ſauyoure Ieſu, that ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones as wyll can it by harte, and haue it ready in mynde may lyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ordre &amp; lay vp as it were trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in a cheſte or cofre, all ſuche maters of the goſpell, &amp; that done appertayne vnto the actes of our ſauyour, as bene preached where they ben preſente, or that they don here any good communycacions or redynges. And alſo ouer this / they ſhall haue two greate profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:5373:102"/> hereby, one is: that no remedy maye better ne ſoner chace awaye all temptacions, &amp; put the ghoſtly enemyes to flyght, than this reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce. The ſeconde is, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge in this worlde may rather ne more ſpedefully moue a dull harte vnto deuotion, &amp; vnto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of vertue, than this exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe. I beſeche you all therfore, in viſceribus Ieſu chriſti: that is to ſay, for the tender loue of our lord god and moſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu: gyue ſome laboure and diligence thervnto, and dayly vſe the ſame. It is but ſhorte and therfore may it ſoone be had by harte. And it is very ſwete, pleaſaunt and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and therfore ſhulde be recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued with god wyll and diligence.</p>
                     <p>¶The ſelfe table of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">The fyr∣ſte. </seg>
                        </label> ¶The Incarnacion, that is:
<pb facs="tcp:5373:102"/> whan (after the ſalutacion &amp; gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angell Gabriell) our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure was conceyued perfite ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; very god, in the wombe of our bleſſed lady Mary, euer virgine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> ¶The Natiuite, that is the bleſſed byrth of our ſauiour whan he was borne in Bethiee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me bleſſed lady, without any pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: ſhe euer remaynyng virgine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> ¶The Circumciſion / whan he fyrſte ſhedde his precyous blode for our redempcion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iiii."/> ¶The Epyphany / whan he was ſhewed and openly declared vnto the hoole worlde by the thre kynges, to be very god, and very man, the ſauyoure of the worlde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> ¶The Preſentacion / that is whan he was brought vnto the temple with oblacion or offrynge accordyng vnto the lawe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the purificacion or churchynge of our Lady.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:103"/>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> ¶The flyght in to Egypte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kynge Herode dyd pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue our ſauyour, and wyllyng ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to ſlee hym, dyde cauſe to ſlee all the Innocent chyldren within the cooſtes &amp; countrey of Bethlee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/> ¶The diſputacion, that was after his retourne and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Egypte agayne, whan he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with his mother and Ioſeph vnto Hieruſalem, &amp; there vnknowynge vnto them remayned and taryed / tyll that thre dayes after, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great ſekynge they founde hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diſputyng amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctours, &amp; than was he .xii. yeres of age.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="viii."/> ¶His humiliacion and meke behauyoure vnto his parentes / that was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he lefte that hyghe place and exerciſe of contemplaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and went with them, and was obedient vnto them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ix."/> ¶ His educacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or bryngynge vp, that was whan he taried and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:103"/> dwelled at Nazareth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bleſſed mother and with Ioſeph her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, euer occupied after theyr wyll and mynde vnto theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe, and euer as he grewe &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in age and ſtatur, ſo dyd he appere and ſhewe hym ſelfe in grace and vertue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="x."/> ¶His Baptyſme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was: whan he was baptiſed of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptiſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flode of Iordane, where the voyce of the father of heuen was herde, and the holy ghoſte (in the kynde and lykenes of a doue) was ſene, whiche dyd teſtifye and declare for trouth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte was god and man, the Meſſie and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure of the worlde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xi."/> ¶Wyldernes, that is: that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly and forthwith after his ſayde baptiſme he was led (by the ſpirite of god) in to a wyldernes / not farre frome the ſayd flode of Iordane, to the ende and purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:104"/> to be attempted of the deuyll.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xii."/> ¶Faſte, that is: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he in the wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes dyd faſte frome all maner of fode, meat or drynke, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of .xl. dayes and fourty nyghtes contynually together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xiii."/> ¶Temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that is: that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly and forthwith after that faſte whan he beganne to waxe hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry, the deuyll dyd tempte him vnto glotonye and vnto pryde / &amp; vnto couetyſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xiiii."/> ¶Victory / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauioure dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founde the deuyll in all his temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; (for our welth) had ouer hym the vyctory &amp; mayſtry.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xv."/> ¶Election / that is: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choſynge of his diſciples, and the appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng and deuydyng of them in to dyuers degrees and ordres.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xvi."/> ¶Preachyng, that was whan he ſpake openly vnto the people / and that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munly in paraboles.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xvii."/> ¶Teachynge / that was whan
<pb facs="tcp:5373:104"/> he taught his diſciples &amp; apoſtles ſecretly by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe ſuche miſteries as apperteyned vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know and not vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xviii,"/> ¶Laboures, that was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wente aboute from towne to tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, from cite to cite, from countrey to countrey, in hunger, thurſte, &amp; colde, and many a wery iourney.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xix."/> ¶Miracles, whiche he dyd in many a ſondry maner. In tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng water in wyne / in fedynge of many thouſandes with a ſmall porcion of vytayle. In curynge &amp; helynge of all maner of ſyckenes &amp; diſeaſes, &amp; in ſhewynge to many theyr ſecrete &amp; inward thoughtes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xx."/> ¶The Maundy / that was the laſte ſouper, that he made to ende and conclude the olde teſtamente / by the paſcal lambe / and to ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; begynne the newe teſtament.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxi."/> ¶The miniſtery or ſeruyce / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was whan he waſſhed the fete of
<pb facs="tcp:5373:105"/> his diſciples ariſynge therunto frome the ſoupper.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxii."/> ¶The Conſecracion, that was whan he retournyng agayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the table, dyd (of bread &amp; wyne) conſecrate &amp; make his owne holy body and ſacred blode, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune and howſell his apoſtles / and gaue them power to conſecrate &amp; make the ſame, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they were all made preaſtes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxiii"/> ¶The ſermone / that was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (after all this) he preached vnto his apoſtles a ſolempne &amp; maruelous ſwete ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> makyng ſpecially me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of loue, vnite, peace, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxiiii."/> ¶Agony / that was whan he went a ſyde from the company, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Peter, ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſaynt Iames / &amp; yet went ſomwhat from them vnto prayer / wherin he ſwet water &amp; blode for agony / fere / ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and trouble of mynde / for the maner of that bytter paſſyon and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:105"/> moſte cruell dethe that he ſawe to come / and howe lytell it ſhulde be regarded and ſet by.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxv."/> ¶Betraynge / that was whan the traytoure Iudas that before had ſolde hym vnto the Iewes / came with a company of harney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed men / &amp; with a falſe flaterynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſhewed vnto them whiche was he.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxvi."/> ¶Takynge / that was whan (after that kyſſe) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoudyers layde hande vpon hym and toke hym / &amp; all his diſciples fledde and forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hym for the tyme.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxvii."/> ¶Byſſhopes / that is whan the ſoudiers that toke hym / brought hym vnto the byſſhopes Anne and Cayphas, where he was exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by falſe wytnes accuſed / and cruelly torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxviii"/> ¶Pylate, that is: that on the morowe he was preſented by the Iewes, &amp; falſly accuſed vnto Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:106"/>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxix."/> ¶Herode / that is: whan Pyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te had examined hym and coulde not fynde hym in any thynge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fauty, than dyd he ſende hym vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Herode the kynge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxx."/> ¶Pylate agayne, that is: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herode had examined hym in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynges / and he wolde anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hym vnto nothynge: than he put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym a whyte foles cote / &amp; with deryſion and mokery ſente hym agayne vnto Pylate.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxi."/> ¶Examinacion, that was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (after many newe falſe accuſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Iewes) he ferther examined hym by longe proceſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxii."/> ¶Flagellacion, that was: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate wyllynge to delyuer hym (bycauſe he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fautles, and yet coulde not ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peaſe the crye and malyce of the Iewes) dyd put hym naked, and tyed him vnto a pyller, and cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:5373:106"/> hym to be cruelly ſcourged, ſo that no place of his body was vntorne or vnwounded.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxiii."/> ¶Coronacion, that was whan the Iewes wolde not yet be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and contente, Pylate cauſed hym to be crowned with a crowne of ſharpe thornes, and with a rede in his hande in ſtede of a ſeptre / &amp; clothed in purpure: brought hym forth amonge them, and ſayde in mockage / Beholde your kynge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxiiii."/> ¶Condempnacion / that was: whan the Iewes wold in nowyſe be otherwyſe contente than with his deth. Pylate ſet in a trone as iudge (condempned him) &amp; iudged hym vnto the deth of the croſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxv."/> ¶Fatigacion / that was: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate hade putt vpon hym his owne clothes agayne / and gyuen the ſayde iugement, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> layde the heuy croſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his necke / vnder the whiche (for very werynes and
<pb facs="tcp:5373:107"/> fayntenes) he fell downe (as not able to bere it any forther) and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſed they another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bere it for hym vnto the place / that was the mounte of Caluary.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxvi"/> ¶Crucifixion, that was: whan he came vnto the place, they cauſed hym to put hym ſelfe naked agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and to ioyne and frame his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vnto the croſſe, whervnto they nayled him with foure great nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">Lib. iiii. reuelat bte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gide cap. lxx. b</note> one through the mydle of hys ryght hande, the ſeconde through the lefte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and through eyther fote one, laynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legges on croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, the one ouerthwarte ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, and ſo dyd they hang hym / &amp; by many rebukes mocked hym / and whan he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playned of thurſt / they gaue hym eyſell &amp; gall. And whan he had ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged ther ſo payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the ſpace of thre houres, he with lowde crye commendyng his ſpirite and ſoule vnto the father
<pb facs="tcp:5373:107"/> of heuen / expired &amp; dyed. And yet after his departynge (to be ſure of his deth) one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſowdyours ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a wounde in his ſyde &amp; thraſte hym vnto the harte with a ſpere.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxvii."/> ¶Sepulture, that is to ſaye: the buryinge, whan Ioſephe ab Aramathie had aſked of Pylate his bleſſed body / he toke hym downe at complyn tyme, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried hym in a newe graue or tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be that he had made for hym ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxviii."/> ¶Reſurrection / that was: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thyrde daye after he dyd aryſe in a gloryous body and ſoule, and appered fyrſt vnto our bleſſed la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy his mother, than vnto Mary magdalene, and after vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre Maries / than vnto ſaynte Peter, and after that vnto two of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples at Emaus. And the ſame nyght vnto ten of the Apoſtles whan all theyr dores and wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes were faſte ſhut and cloſed
<pb facs="tcp:5373:108"/> vp. Thus you maye perceyue he dyd appere .v. tymes that ſame daye of his reſurrection.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxix."/> ¶Aſcencion / that was: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he (in many ſondry wyſes, by many apperynges) had ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; aſſured his gloryous reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, by the ſpace of .xl. dayes: than in the preſence of his mother his apoſtles, and in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of many other diſciples, men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: he dyd meruelouſly aſcende and ſtye vp into heuen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/> ¶The Miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſendyng of the holy ghoſt, that was whan the .x. day after the ſayd meruelouſe aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion accordyng vnto his promyſe he ſent downe the holy ghoſt vnto his bleſſed mother / his apoſtles &amp; diſciples, wherby they were all fulfylled with grace, &amp; confyrmed theryn, as the fyrſte churche of chriſte, and ſo hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynued / and doth &amp; ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche
<pb facs="tcp:5373:108"/> vnto the ende of the worlde. Amen. ¶you now wyll thynke this table ouer lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for a dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, but you muſte reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that the ſelfe table is conteyned in the fyrſt wordes of euery artycle, and the reſydue is a breue declaracion of the ſame, &amp; therfore I ſhall be contente to ſet it out alone in ſelfe wordes, whiche ben in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mbre .xl.</p>
                     <p>¶Thus.</p>
                     <p>¶Incarnation / Natiuite / Cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſion / Epypham / Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / Egypte / Diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Educacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Baptyſme / Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes / Faſte, Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Victory / Electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Preachyng / Teachyng / Laboures / Miracles / Maundy / Miniſtery / Conſecracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Agonye / Betraynge / Takynge / Biſſhopes / Pylate / Herode / Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late agayne / Examinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Flagel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacion / Coronacion / Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / Fatigation / Crucifixio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture
<pb facs="tcp:5373:109"/>
/ Reſurrection / Aſcention / Miſſion.</p>
                     <p>¶ The ende.</p>
                     <p>¶ Nowe you may ſe this table is not long, but may eaſely be had by harte, and if it ſo be, and dayly vſed: I dare well ſay the perſones ſhall fynde conforte therin, bothe to exclude vyce / &amp; alſo to encreaſe in vertu &amp; grace. And yet forther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue therin vnto theyr conforte &amp; ioye euerlaſtyng wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto he bryng vs that bought vs our lord god and moſt ſwete ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Ieſu, who guyde you &amp; kepe you all. Amen.</p>
                     <p>¶The houſholder.</p>
                     <p>¶ Thus haue I nowe (in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargynge of my coſcience) done &amp; fulfylled the cownſell &amp; byddynge of my ghoſtly father that taught me thys leſſon, whiche cownſell was, that I ſhulde call you all by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me: as well my wyfe and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:109"/> as myne other ſeruauntes, men / women, and chyldren, and to teche you thys ſayd and ſame leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he taught me. Now I pray you all and charge you to do your deuoyr and diligence to followe it and vſe it.</p>
                     <p>¶ Alſo he delyuered vnto me an other prety leſſon, whiche was not his owne werke, but of his tranſlation as foloweth, and bad me alſo teche it you.</p>
                     <p>¶ A breue or ſhorte monycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or counſeyle of the cure and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of a houſholde, accordyng vnto policy. Take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of a pyſtle of a great lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, called Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narde Silueſtre, &amp; put amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> werkes of ſaynt Bernarde for by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that many done iudge and thynke hit was his owne werke.</p>
                     <p>Set forth by the ſame brother.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:5373:110"/>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte good deuoute chriſtians / take mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte hede, and gyue moſte dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre your ſelfe and all youres, vnto our lorde, accordyng vnto the poore leſſon that goeth before / and than ſe well vnto the ſubſtaunce / and guydyng of your houſe / and goodes. Se fyrſt that peace be in the houſe / and that you agre all together / for els all your goodes wyll ſone goo to naught. Than (after the commune prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be) cut your tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges: after, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vnto your ledder. Spende accordynge vnto your gaynes / gettynges / or re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / and not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. It is alſo good policy / to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue one yeres rente / or a yeres gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in ſtore for chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, whiche is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto chriſtianite whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re extreme, or very ſtreyte nede / is not perceyued in the neyghbour. A
<pb facs="tcp:5373:110"/> neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or rechles ꝑſone may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſet on fyre, &amp; deſtroye great ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Haue therfore a good eye / and garde vnto the diligence of your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, for vnder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your goodes may ſoone mynuſhe / and be waſted before you knowe / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware or haue knowlege therof / If your goodes begynne to waſte better is, &amp; leſſe rebuke for you to abſteyne, &amp; withdrawe your char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / than to fall in to nedynes / or daunger. An olde prouerbe. Qui plus expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> copia tendit. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admiretur ſi paupertate gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetur. That is. ⚜ Who ſo done ſpende beyonde theyr faculte / No meruayle thoughe with nede they greued be.</p>
                     <p>¶ It is therfore a great prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, &amp; good foreſyght ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare your goodes, and your gaynes with your expenſes. Ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ouerſe your goodes, ſhalbe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.
<pb facs="tcp:5373:111"/> For your beaſtes maye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hurte for defaute of fode, all though they nothynge aſke ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne.<note place="margin">Ariſtotl. i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Econo.</note> The ſtepp of the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: maketh a fatte donghyll. And the eye of the mayſter: a fatte horſe. that is to meane. that the preſence of the mayſter: in euery corner / is moche profytable. Sumptuous &amp; coſtly weddynges or brydales: be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> damage / without honoure. Expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warre: ben more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, than profytable. Better is to ſuffre ſome wronge, &amp; to bye peace, than to make warre, or to kepe warre. Coſte made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall perſones? is clerely loſte. Coſte made vpon kynne, frendes? is reſonable. Fede your houſholde ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: with honeſt commune fare / without delicates. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte that is made a gloto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall neuer after mende his maners. Glotony is vyle, fylthy, and ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng,
<pb facs="tcp:5373:111"/> and wyll make the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and careles perſone ſoone roten &amp; ſhorte lyued.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. xxxi.</note> Meane fedyng with ſcarcite: is vnto the diligent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone / pleaſaunte and profytable. vpon the holydayes &amp; hyghe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes: gyue your houſholde plenty of meate, but ſeldome &amp; fewe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates. For the vſe of delicate fode / wyll ſoone marre a good ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Let glotony and thy purſe ſtryue, and go to lawe together: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thou well, whiche parte thou takeſt, but for the moſte parte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way holde with the purſe. For glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, men of lawe, and wytneſſes / done ſpeke all of affection, but the purſe bryngeth in playn euidence and profe, the empte barne and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empte bagge. But if very negar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhut vp thy purſe, than arte not thou an euen iudge. For nygardy is a folyſihe and nedeles fere / and euer lyuynge in pouerte, &amp; hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:5373:112"/> &amp; muckereth vp: he can not tell for whome. If you haue ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of corne deſyre no derth. For thoſe perſones that of couetous mynde done procure or deſyre derth, done procure &amp; deſyre the deth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and ſhalbe accuſed: as homici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſteers. Sell thy corne bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter chepe vnto thy neyghbure (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thouhg he were thyne enemye) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers. For an enemye is ſomtyme ſoner vaynquyſſhed and ouercomen by a kynde dede / than by the ſwerde. Be neuer at debate with thy neyghbure, but rather ſtudy / &amp; laboure to be at one. For y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt haue none ſo ſure a caſtel / or garde of thy lyfe: as is the loue and frendſhype of thy neghbure. If thou ſuſpecte the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy houſe: let other perſones rather ſhewe the / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhulde be ouer bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to try out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater. For though it were of thyne owne wyfe / or the
<pb facs="tcp:5373:112"/> wyfe of the huſbande: it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ones knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is neuer cured / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounde is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out remedy. If any remedy be: it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be whan lyke chaunce is herde of other ꝑſones. The leſt &amp; moſt eaſy way therin: is to diſſimule the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter though it were pryuely knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and pretende ygnorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without any quarell or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a dyſcrete ghoſtly father let the parties be reformed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſynne be not contynued. A noble harte / &amp; hygh gentyll mynde: wyll neuer ſerche of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s maters. A ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ew wyll ſoner be corrected by ſmyling or laughynge: than by a ſtaffe / or ſtrokes. The beſte way to kepe a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good: is gentyll intreaty, &amp; neuer to let her knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected / &amp; euer to be counſeyled &amp; informed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> louing maner. An ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de woman vnclene of lyuyng (if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe wolde ſuffre) ſhuld be buried
<pb facs="tcp:5373:113"/> quycke. Let your clothynge or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,<note place="margin">Of aray.</note> be in a meane, nor vyle ne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous, but alway, fayre &amp; honeſt / and of ſad: and not of wanton faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyon. A coſtly garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te beyonde: or aboue the ſtate and degre of the perſone: is a ſygne and toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell wytte. For a woman that hath ſuffyciente araye: to deſyre newe / and chaunge: is a ſynge of lytell ſadnes. ⚜ Truſte hym rather for thy frende, that ſomwhat doth for the: than hym that doth offre hym ſelfe: ſaynge. I am yours in all I can &amp; may. For in wordes is great plenty of frendes.<note place="margin">Prouerb xvii. c</note> * A true frende loueth at all tymes, and neuer fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth at nede. There is no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſon of ryches: vnto a faythfull frende.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. ſ. v</note> Neuer repute, ne thynke hym thy frende that doth prayſe / or boſte the vnto thy face, or in thy preſence. Whan you gyue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyle vnto a fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: ſay this ſemeth
<pb facs="tcp:5373:113"/> beſt vnto me, not thus you muſte nedely do. For you may ſoner get rebuke, or blame for your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle if it proue not: than tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke for your good counſeyle: though it ſpede well. If mynſtreles, iogulers, or geſters, come vnto thy houſe: ſaye thou haſte no lodgynge for ſuche geſtes / you kepe neyther Inne nor aleſtake. For if you take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in theyr paſtymes: you bene full lyke to haue a nother wyfe ſhortly after, whoſe name is called pouerte, or beggry. If you fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to come wher they ben, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne ſomwhat to delecte in theyr maters: I aduyſe you diſſymule &amp; take vpon you that you herde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not / ne ſet any thynge therby. For if they perceue &amp; ſe you but laugh: they wyl take that for an erneſt to crye largeſſe / and to haue reward. And ſo importune wyll they be / &amp; ſo ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully craue: that you ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:5373:114"/> yrke and wery of them, &amp; peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they wyll fall to rebukynge / braulynge, and ſcoldynge, ſo that you ſhalbe fayne &amp; glade, to gyue ſomwhat (for fere) vnto thoſe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe clappers, worthy in dede to be hanged vp. For I tell you, god is not pleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that occupacion: except it be (as ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tolerable or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable) among prynces, lordes / and hyghe eſtates.</p>
                     <p>Now for your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, if you ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hyghe proude myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; ſtubburne ſtomake, put hym away leſt after he do you harme, &amp; ſo do hym that alway doth prayſe your maners in all thinges. For a flaterer is worſe than an enemye: your enemy can not lyghtly decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue you, but your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or your neyghbours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do prayſe you bene ſurely aboute to deceyue you.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. vii. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> xxxiii. d</note> If you haue a baſſhefull &amp; dredefull ſeruaunte &amp; fynde hym faythfull / 
<pb facs="tcp:5373:114"/> than loue hym &amp; cheryſſhe hym as your owne naturall chyld. Make your buyldynges rather for nede than for pleſure. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appetyte of buyldyng for pleaſure ſhall neuer haue ende, tyll pouerte teche wyt: ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what to late. Be loth to ſell your herytage, &amp; if you muſte nede ſell? Sell not vnto great perſones, but rather for leſſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lower perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Better is to ſell, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to borow by vſury. For vſury is lyke a thefe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolde warne you before: what harm he wold do vnto you. If you bye or bergayn, be not butyfellow w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great perſones. And though he be vnder you, yet ſtryue not with hym leſte he put his parte vnto your better, or maſter. In all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges kepe truely &amp; faythfully your bonde &amp; promyſe, accordyng vnto your couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. Due temperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is a thynge of greate honeſty in a houſhold, let therfore your drynke
<pb facs="tcp:5373:115"/> wyne / ale / or bere / be temperate. Strong drynke is more pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / than holſome.<note place="margin">Eccleſi xxxi. d</note> The wyſe man ſayth, that ſobre drynke is the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the both of ſoul and body.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> And the wiſe &amp; lerned perſone wyl be ryght well contente with lytell drynke: &amp; that ſhall not trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomake / but rather cauſe ſwete and holſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſlepe: and of the contrary done come many inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytes as there doth folowe. Who ſo euer among many &amp; dyuers ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge drynkes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof: is ſobre / may be called an erthly god, or a god vpon erth, wraſtle not therwith if you do my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell. And if by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce you be in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, &amp; begynne to fele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drynke werke: aryſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte: a ſlepe is more mete for you than any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. Who ſo by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wolde excuſe dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kennes: doth openly declare his owne diſeaſe. The knowlege &amp; iugement of wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:
<pb facs="tcp:5373:115"/> doth nothyng become a yong ꝑſone. If a phyſicion or ſurgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe to be dronke, let him not haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of your diſeaſe ne let none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take experience, and lerne in you / howe to cure or hele a nother. For though they be well lerned / &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not experience: it is no wiſedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue theyr connyng vpon you. Great gaye horſes, and lytell preaty dogges: leue you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lordes &amp; ladyes. A byg labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng horſe, &amp; a maſtyfe, or a curre dogge: ben good to kepe your hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. As for haukes, houndes &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng dogges do ſpende more than they done get, they ben mete and accordyng for ſtates: to ſet ydle ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes on werke, but farre vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng ben they, for huſbandes &amp; ware houſholders. It is no wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to make your owne chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtewardes or rulers of your houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold or goodes. Foles &amp; neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:5373:116"/> or careles ꝑſones, haile many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. For that is theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne excuſe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thyng is wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g they ſay tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that chaunce or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune was cauſe therof. I ſaye not nay: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaunce or myſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune may fall. But who ſo doth fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low wyſdome, lernyng, &amp; diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſeldome accuſe myſfortune. For dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t warenes, &amp; good hede, done ſeldom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myſfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. But yet more ſeldom ſhall you ſe myſfortune &amp; ſlouth or neglyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, departed in fondre, for they do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany together. The ſluggard ſaythe, god wyll helpe hym, &amp; ſo longe he truſteth thervn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to,<note place="margin">Prouer. vi.</note> tyll he be brought vnto beggry For god by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe man doth ſende the ſluggarde (for example) vnto the Ant or pyſmere,<note place="margin">Iob. v.</note> to lerne to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure. For man (ſayth Iob (is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto laboure, as a byrd to flye. Kepe you (therfore) but fewe ydle
<pb facs="tcp:5373:116"/> perſones or men. And watche you well &amp; take good hede vnto euery ꝑſone of your houſe. And euer po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, weye, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydre your expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your gaynes or gettynges. Fyrſt get and bryng in, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. For it is no good huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry to borow. And whan you waxe aged truſte rather vnto god than vnto your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. That you ſede before you, you ſhalbe ſure to fynde. No cofre, cheſte, ne towre may be more ſure to kepe treaſure? than is heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let not (therfore) the poore paſſe you. What you gyue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: you gyue vnto Chriſte. And of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you leue behynd you: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt vnto euery ꝑſone his parte. For better were it for you nothing to leue: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtryfe &amp; debate ſhuld be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce blamyſſhed &amp; god offended for your goodes. Truſte them beſt to do for your ſoule: not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done loue, or ſay they done loue
<pb facs="tcp:5373:117"/> your ſoule, but that you done per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, and coniecture, done loue theyr owne ſoule. Make your teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mente euery yere newe, &amp; ſurely ſealed by wytnes. Laye it where (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede is) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ay be founde, no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> howe to ende his life. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſure way, to dye well, is well to lyue. Whiche he graunte vs, that bought vs, our lord god, &amp; moſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu chriſte. Amen. Of your charyte pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame olde wretche of Syon. Rycharde whytforde.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ Imprynted by me Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande / At London within temple barre. At the ſygne of the blew garlande / Frome the temple gate not farre.</p>
                  <p>An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. M.CCCCC. &amp; xxxvii.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
